<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation to repentance, and union among Protestants, or, A discourse upon the burden of Dumah</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18188951</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18188951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1130:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation to repentance, and union among Protestants, or, A discourse upon the burden of Dumah</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Widow Swart ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVIII [1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: J. Shower.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Shower by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXI, 11-12 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Protestantism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An Exhortation to</hi> Repentance, <hi>and</hi> Union <hi>among</hi> PROTESTANTS. OR A DISCOURSE Upon The BURDEN of DUMAH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſaiah. <hi>XXI. 11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He calleth to me out of <hi>Seir, Watchman,</hi> what of the Night? <hi>Watchman,</hi> what of the Night? The Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaid, the <hi>Morning</hi> cometh, and alſo the <hi>Night:</hi> if ye will Enquire, <hi>Enquire</hi> ye: Return, Come.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. 12.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> Every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, is brought to deſolation; and every City or Houſe divided againſt it ſelf, shall not ſtand.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 2. 1-4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> If there be therefore any Conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any Fellowship of the ſpirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind. Let nothing be done thro ſtrife or vain glory, but in lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves. Look not every man at his own things, but every man alſo at the things of others.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AMSTERDAM, Printed for the <hi>Widow Swart,</hi> near the Exchange. Anno, MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106978:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106978:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Danger, which threatens the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> at this day is ſo viſible to every Eye, that 'twere a needleſs Labour to prove it. All the <hi>Symptoms</hi> that appear in the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> ſeem to preſage and ſignifie a diſmal <hi>Criſis.</hi>
'Tis not poſſible, I confeſs, to make a certain Concluſion about the Event; neither is it our Duty to attempt it: But if the Cauſe of the <hi>Reformation</hi> from <hi>Popery</hi> be really ſo valuable and dear to us, as we profeſs; Every <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is obliged to afford his utmoſt Aſſiſtance for its preſervation. There are very many who think, this is ſufficiently ſecured by wiſe <hi>Laws,</hi> and learned <hi>Diſputations;</hi> both which have their uſe, but will never of themſelves be ſufficient to ſuch an End. Inward <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> are requiſite to ſecure a Doctrine, which bears thoſe Characters. If our Religion were of an <hi>Earthly</hi> Original and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, it might he defended well enough by Human ſtrength and Policie, and ſuch methods as <hi>Rome Pagan</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> have found Neceſſary for the ſupport of their Hierarchy. But a Doctrine which comes from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and leads thither, muſt have its chief ſupport from thence, and will be beſt maintain'd by a ſerious complyance with its Holy Deſign. And therefore after all the Books of Controverſie, wherby the falſe Principles of <hi>Popery</hi> have been expos'd and baffled, nothing but the <hi>Love</hi> of Truth, and <hi>Obedience</hi> to it, will be found an effectual <hi>Bulwark</hi> againſt the Corruptions and Deſigns of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> There is no wicked man but needs ſuch an <hi>Opium</hi> as <hi>Popery</hi> to quiet his Conſcience, and reconcile a ſenſual ungodly Life with the Hopes of Heaven. He hath already receiv'd many Errors for Truth, and ſo is prepared to admit more: He is deſtitute of that which should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, him from Deluſion: He never had any <hi>Experience</hi> of the Efficacy, and Certainty, the Truth and Power of the Principles of Religion, that should ſettle and eſtablish him: He hath not that <hi>Affection</hi> to divine Truth, that should make him diligent in ſearching after it; or that <hi>Purity</hi> of Heart which might enable him to receive the beams of Heavenly light. 'Tis only by the practical fear of God, or the keeping of his Commandments, that any can be aſſured to be <hi>taught of God.</hi> So that the moſt certain way to keep the <hi>Faith,</hi> is to keep <hi>a good Conſcience</hi> towards God and men.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, there is no ſuch <hi>Preparation</hi> for <hi>Popery</hi> and other dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Errors as a wicked Heart and Life. When men <hi>receive not the Truth in the love of it, God ſends them ſtrong Deluſions to believe</hi> Lies. If men are falſe and unfaithful to the Common Principles of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> if they
<pb facs="tcp:106978:3"/>reſiſt the Light, and rebel againſt it; if they hold the Truth in unrighteouſneſs; and debauch their Conſciences by a vicious practice; they muſt needs dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relish and diſlike Holy Truth: and having forfeited the Aſſiſtance of God, they are prepared for <hi>Sadduciſm, Deiſm,</hi> or <hi>Popery.</hi> Theſe Deluſions do or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily enter at this back door. Men are ſenſual, <hi>not having the ſpirit,</hi> and then the Doctrines of the Goſpel are <hi>Fooliſhneſs</hi> to them. This Conſideration will both juſtifie the Providence of God, in permitting ſo many to be thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, and doth let us know what we are to expect concerning the <hi>Generality</hi> of Looſe and Carnal <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> how unlikely they are to hold faſt their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, if called to ſuffer much for it. They are built upon the Sand, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for <hi>Deluſion;</hi> and no wonder if they are blown up and down by every wind of Falſe Doctrine; or toſſed to and fro from <hi>one</hi> Religion to <hi>another,</hi> as to their <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> when they have really none at all in the <hi>Practice.</hi> This method the <hi>Romiſh Emiſſaries</hi> have taken in all the Courts and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Europe,</hi> where they could have Admiſſion: After the ſame manner that the <hi>Devil</hi> leads men to <hi>Hell,</hi> have they endeavor'd to bring men over to <hi>their Church;</hi> viz. by gratifying the Luſts of men, and promoting voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſenſuality, that mens <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings being clouded, they might not diſcern the <hi>Cheats</hi> and <hi>Impoſtures</hi> of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural Doctrines and Worship.</p>
            <p>It is therefore the great Intereſt of all true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (who taking the H. Scriptures for the only Rule of their Faith, deſires, and duty, have the ſame objective Religion, and are all of one Church,) to endeavor every one to <hi>live better,</hi> and to promote ſerious <hi>Godlineſs</hi> among others; eſpecially if we are under any apprehenſions and fears of the threatning Anger of God againſt us for the want of it. An <hi>Union in this</hi> would make it eaſy for us to bear with one onother in Love, notwithſtanding all our leſſer Differences.</p>
            <p>This being recommended in the following Diſcourſe, when the ſubſtance of it was not long ſince preacht to the <hi>Engliſh Congregation</hi> here, the Printing of it was judg'd might be of ſome uſe, and to that end was deſired by ſeveral. For the ſake of our Brethren in <hi>England</hi> I have enlarged the latter part, as I did the former on another account. I am ſenſible, I have adventured the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing of many with the Hope that I may profit ſome; however, declaring my readineſs and deſire by further Light to be better inform'd, and praying for the <hi>Peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> I recommend it to the Bleſſing of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Shower.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Rotterdam</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 20/30. 1688.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106978:3"/>
            <head>THE BURDEN OF DUMAH OR A <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> upon thoſe words of the Prophet,</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Iſaiah, <hi>XXI. 11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>The Burden of <hi>Dumah.</hi> He calleth to me out of <hi>Seir,</hi> Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night? The Watchman ſaid, the morning cometh, and alſo the night: if ye will Enquire, Enquire ye: Return, come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great difference among Interpreters is, whether by <hi>Dumah</hi> be meant the Country of the <hi>Ishmaelites,</hi> or that of the <hi>Idumeans;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 24.14.</note> whether the Race of ſcoffing <hi>Ishmael,</hi> or the Poſterity of prophane <hi>Eſau.</hi> We read of one of <hi>Ishmael's</hi> Sons of that name, and that part of <hi>Arabia,</hi> where he ſeated himſelf, was called <hi>Dumah</hi> on that account. But the following expreſſion, <hi>One calleth to me out of Seir,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.3, 4.</note> makes it more probable that the <hi>Edomites</hi> or <hi>Idumeans</hi> are underſtood, <hi>Seir</hi> being <hi>the Land of Eſau,</hi> or <hi>the Country of Edom,</hi> which God gave to <hi>Eſau</hi> and his Poſterity, and would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſo much as to paſs thro it, without their leave;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106978:4"/>which <hi>Moſes</hi> requeſted as their neareſt way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> but it was denied 'em, <note place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and they paſſed by the borders of <hi>Idumea,</hi> without entring into it.</p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of this and ſeveral other places of H. Scripture, I ſhall premiſe ſomewhat, 1. Concerning <hi>Eſau.</hi> 2. His <hi>Country.</hi> 3. The <hi>Idumeans,</hi> his Poſterity.</p>
            <p>§ 1. Of <hi>Eſau,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and Father of the <hi>Idume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> we read that he is called <hi>Edom. Gen.</hi> 25. v. 30. Eſau, <hi>quaſi Factus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.25. Joſeph: An tiq: lib. 2. c. 1.</note> ſaith <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Lightfoot,</hi> being born <hi>Hairy,</hi> as if he had been of mature Age: or <hi>Edom, red,</hi> from the <hi>Colour</hi> of his Hair. And afterwards that name was confirm'd to him on the Sale of his Birthright, for <hi>a meſs of red pottage,</hi> to his Brother <hi>Iacob.</hi> The Contentions and Enmity that ſhould happen between the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the two Brothers was preſignified by their ſtruggling in their Mother's Womb. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto</hi> Rebecca, <hi>two Nations are in thy Womb, and two manner of People shall be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thy Bowels; and the one shall be ſtronger than the other, and the Elder</hi> (Eſau) <hi>shall ſerve the Younger.</hi> This Oracle ſhe kept in her mind, and ſo firmly believ'd it, that when <hi>Iacob</hi> ſcrupled to follow her Counſel, as to the manner of obtaining his Father's Bleſſing, leſt inſtead of it, (being diſcovered) he ſhould meet with a Curſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.12, 13.</note> ſhe tells him, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon me be thy Curſe, my ſon, only obey my voice.</hi> It is not improbable that ſhe ſeared leſt the whole Family might otherwiſe be excluded from the Bleſſing of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> apprehending, that God might juſtly diſannul the promiſe, as to <hi>Eſau,</hi> becauſe of his <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> which he diſcovered, not only by the contempt of the Bleſſing, in ſelling his ſhare in it, and right to it, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.34, 35.</note> with his Birthright, for ſo ſmall a matter, butin his whole Converſation, eſpecially by his Marriage among the <hi>Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites,</hi> who were under the Curſe of God, and to be rooted out. Concerning one of Eſau's Wives, 'tis ſaid expreſly, that ſhe was a Daughter of <hi>Ishmael;</hi> and by that marriage, (againſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Parents, as is intimated by their grief and concern at it,) He endeavored to eſtabliſh the Pretenſions and Plea of <hi>Ishmael,</hi> the ſon of the Bondwoman, for the Bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to the excluſion of his Father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heidegeri</hi> Hiſt. Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch: de Eſavo. Diſſert. 12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.12. 21.</note> in whoſe line God had fixt it.</p>
            <p>§ 2. Concerning the <hi>Country</hi> of <hi>Pſau.</hi> He at firſt inhabited the Eaſtern part of <hi>Idumea,</hi> and therein <hi>Mount Seir,</hi> or <hi>the Land of Seir,</hi> as 'tis called, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.3. But before <hi>Iſrael</hi> came out of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106978:4"/>his Poſterity ſlew the <hi>Horites</hi> or <hi>Horims,</hi> of the race of <hi>Cham,</hi> (who inhabited the ſouthern part) and ſo poſſeſſed themſelves of all <hi>Idumea</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemii F. Hiſt. Jobi: c. 4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.</note> By the <hi>South</hi> is ſometimes meant <hi>Idumea,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with the Southern part of <hi>Iudaea. Eſau</hi> dwelt in <hi>Seir</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the death of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> for from thence he came in an Hoſtile manner to meet his Brother <hi>Iacob,</hi> returning from <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> whither he had retired, after he got the Bleſſing, to avoid the Revenge which his Brother threatned. Upon their Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation <hi>Eſau</hi> returns to <hi>Scir. Gen.</hi> 32.16. He came afterwards with his Family to <hi>Hebron;</hi> and was there with his Brother, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 36.6, 7, 8.</note> at the Death and Funerals of their Father <hi>Iſaac.</hi> But ſuch was the Increaſe of the two Families, that the Land could not bear them both; there was not ſufficient Paſtorage for their Cattel: therefore <hi>Eſau</hi> departed with his Family and Subſtance, and went to <hi>Mount Seir,</hi> and there remained the reſt of his Life.</p>
            <p>He being the Prince of that Country, <note place="margin">Mare ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum, mare Erithraeum, vel mare Idumaeum, ab Edomo vel Erithro. N. <hi>Fulleri Miſe</hi> 5. lib. 4 cap. 20.</note> the adjoyning Red-ſea had its name from him. <hi>Solomon</hi> is ſaid to have ſent ſhips to <hi>Ophir, on the banks of the Red ſea, in the Land of Edom,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 26. The Country o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Idumea</hi> is commonly divided into the <hi>Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Leſſer:</hi> the former ſwallowed up; (ſaith
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Decas cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragr. marco praef § 1. &amp; 5 <hi>Spanhemii</hi> Hiſt. Jobi. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Dr. Lightfoot</hi>) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and the Leſſer or new <hi>Idumea</hi> is mention'd by the Evangeliſt <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. c. 8. which at length was a part of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> as poſſeſſed by the <hi>Idumeans,</hi> after they were Proſelites to the Jewiſh Religion. A <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Steph. Morin:</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: de cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: &amp; He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braeorum.</note> learned man hath lately attempted to prove the <hi>Phaenicians</hi> and <hi>Idumeans</hi> to be all one: <hi>Phaenices dicti quaſi Idumaei, &amp; rubri a mari Edom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 3. Concerning the <hi>Edomites</hi> or <hi>Idumeans,</hi> (who bordered on <hi>Indaea,</hi> as did the <hi>Moabites, Ammonites,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ishmaelites,</hi>) three things are obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That notwithſtanding their Agreement in <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> yet the Jealouſies and Contentions between them and the <hi>Iows</hi> were irreconcileable. They lookt upon their Father <hi>Eſau</hi> as the <hi>Firſtborn,</hi> and that by the priviledge of Primogeniture, the premiſed Bleſſing of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould come in his line: rival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> as having no Right unto it, but by <hi>Iacob's</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting their Father <hi>Eſau.</hi> But God had particularly promiſed that Bieſſing to the line of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob.</hi> On this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he is ſo often ſtiled, <hi>the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>the God of Iacob,</hi> to denote a ſpecial Relation to the <hi>Iews</hi> as his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106978:5"/>peculiar people, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr. Alliae</hi> Reflexions ſur le Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat: part. 2. chap. 15.</note> in oppoſition to the pretences of all their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. The God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and not of <hi>Lot,</hi> againſt the <hi>Moa bites,</hi> who deſcending from <hi>Lot</hi> pretended to the Bleſſing of the promiſed ſeed in that line. The God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and not of <hi>Ishmael,</hi> againſt the <hi>Ishmaelites,</hi> who to the like purpoſe pleaded the Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture of their Father <hi>Ishmael.</hi> The God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and not of <hi>Eſau,</hi> to exclude the <hi>Idumeans,</hi> of the race of <hi>Eſau,</hi> who therefore hated the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and were always Jealous of them.</p>
            <p>Some conformity and agreement in Sacraments among <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> we find by Experience, doth rather produce Jealouſie, than procure love. The differences in other things are therefore thought the more unreaſonable, and hard to be born by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering parties, and are the more inſiſted on to the exaſperating of one another. Inſtances of the like may be given in the diſcord between the <hi>Iews</hi> and the <hi>Samaritans. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphanii</hi> opera. Tom. 2. lib. 1. Hz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. 29.</note> Epiphanius</hi> takes notice of the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> who acknowledged J. Chriſt, but withal continued the Cuſtoms and Ceremonies of the <hi>Iews,</hi> that ſuch was the hatred of the <hi>Iews</hi> againſt them, that they did ſolemnly curſe'em three times a day in their Synagogues. The <hi>Turks</hi> have an honourable Eſteem of our Saviour J. Chriſt, which the <hi>Tartars</hi> have not, yet the <hi>latter</hi> imbrace the Chriſtian Faith ſooner than the <hi>Turks.</hi> So for the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> tho both are <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> and both Circumciſed, they yet deteſt one another more than they do the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and will ſooner permit the Chriſtians to live among them, than tolerate one another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would farther obſerve, that the Hatred and Enmity of the <hi>Idumeans</hi> againſt the <hi>Iews,</hi> did on all occaſions diſcover it ſelf, till the time of the <hi>Macchabees.</hi> Not only did they deny them a paſſage thro their Country,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Namb.</hi> 22.</note> but they took all opportunities to joyn with their Enemies, to ravage and ſpoil them. When <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> burnt the City and Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.</note> the <hi>Edomites</hi> (with others who ſerv'd under him) rejoyc't in its Ruin, and aſſiſted the <hi>Chaldae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> They cried, <hi>Raze it, Raze it, even to the ground. Pſalm.</hi> 137. v. 7. Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the <hi>Chaldaean</hi> Army like Ravens to feed upon the Carcaſſes, which fell by their Cruelty: &amp; taking the advantage of their miſeries, to be Revenged upon them. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.12: 15.</note> For which God threatens to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on <hi>Edom.</hi> Of this the Church profeſſeth her Confidence, 60 <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 49. c. 8.</note> 8. <hi>God hath ſpoken in his Holineſs — over</hi> Edom <hi>will I caſt out my shoe.</hi> Tis an Emblem of ſubduing them under his <hi>feet. I will
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106978:5"/>walk thro poſſeſs, &amp; tread down the land</hi> of Edom: which was true when <hi>David put garriſons in Edom, and all they of Edom became his ſervants.</hi> He penned this Pſalm, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.14.</note> when his General <hi>Ioab</hi> ſmote <hi>twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> Edomites or <hi>Idumeans,</hi> in the Valley of Salt, and <hi>Abiſhai ſix thouſand;</hi> and therfore called <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18:12.</note> 
               <hi>Eighteen thouſand.</hi> They are called <hi>Syrians</hi> in one place, and <hi>Edomites</hi> in another.</p>
            <p>During the captivity of the Jews in <hi>Babylon,</hi> 'tis thought the <hi>Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>means</hi> did invade thoſe parts of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> that were next adjoyning to their Country and fixed there, till rooted out by the <hi>Macchabees.</hi> They ſerved the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (the Seed of <hi>Iacob</hi>) for about <hi>ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> years: and had no proper <hi>King</hi> of their own, till the time of <hi>Iehoram,</hi> when they caſt off the yoke of <hi>Judah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.20.</note> Every Vice-roy was called a King till that time. So we read, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.47. <hi>There was no King in Edom, a Deputy was King:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was foretold by old <hi>Iſaac,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. c. 40. <hi>Joſeph: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq</hi> lib. 8. c. 8 l. 9. c. 2.</note> that the Time ſhould come when <hi>Eſau should have the Dominion, &amp; break the Yoke of</hi> Jacob <hi>from off his neck.</hi> This began in <hi>Solomons</hi> time (when he forſook God, and turned to Idolatry) by <hi>Hadad,</hi> who fled to <hi>Aegypt</hi> for ſhelter, when <hi>Ioabs</hi> Army conquered <hi>Idumea;</hi> afterwards under <hi>Iehoram,</hi> they wholly revolted, and ſlew their King, who had been ſubject to <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> the Father of <hi>Iekoram.</hi> For about eight hundred years they continued a free People, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> lib. 13. c. 17.</note> till the time of <hi>Johannes Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Simon</hi> the Macchabee, who forced and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled them to receive Circumciſion and the Religious Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Jews.</hi> This was one of the firſt Inſtances of <hi>Force</hi> uſed in the matter of Religion, which as it was a ſymptom of the degenerate State of the <hi>Iewish</hi> Church at that time, ſo it was attended with the ordinary Conſequent of ſuch Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, viz. inſtead of making the <hi>Idumaeans</hi> ſincere Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the <hi>Iewish</hi> Religion, it did but exaſperate them the more againſt their Religion and Nation. 'T was an Evidence the Spirit of God had greatly forſaken the <hi>Iews</hi> under the ſecond Temple; and it ſucceeded accordingly: for the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were lately his Favorites, and ſuggeſted that Counſel to <hi>Hircanus;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid</hi> lib. 13. c. 18; 19.</note> and put him upon it, were the next whom he ſeverely proceeded againſt; for under the moſt grievous penalties he forbad (and endeavor'd to abolish) their <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and within a few years, the very Family of <hi>Hircanus</hi> too, (by contentions and quarrels among themſelves) was extinquiſht, and by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106978:6"/>righteous Judgment of God, the Government of the <hi>Iews</hi> fell into the hands of the <hi>Idumeans,</hi> when ſuch as <hi>Antipater</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> ruled over them. After this the Jews were more careful, as well they might, not to make Proſelytes to their Religion by fraud or Force, or to admit any but ſuch as offered themſelves freely, of their own accord.</p>
            <p>From that time the <hi>Idumeans</hi> were comprehended among the <hi>Iews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Light foot,</hi> centur: Choragr. Matth. praem. cap 3</note> and <hi>Idumea</hi> began to be confounded with <hi>Iudea,</hi> and reckon'd as a part of <hi>Palleſtine. Balaam's</hi> prophecy had now been fullfilled, <hi>that Edom should be a Poſſeſsion, and</hi> Seir <hi>a Poſſeſsion for his Enemies.</hi> 24. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. They were now reputed as <hi>Iews,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Antipater,</hi> of an <hi>Idumean</hi> ſtock, being the ſon of Parents who were Proſelites, might be called the <hi>Brother</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and being by profeſſion a <hi>Iew,</hi> and ſtanding in the third Generation, might enter into the Congregation, and be their King. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeth</hi> de bello Jud. lib. 1. c. 15. <hi>Spanhemii</hi> dub. Evang. pars. 1. dub. 16. De Herodis M. genere. <hi>Cauſabon</hi> Exercit. 1. ad appar. Baron.</note> 
               <hi>Herod's</hi> family, of the race o' <hi>Edom,</hi> did by leave of the <hi>Romans</hi> reign over the <hi>Iews</hi> for the ſpace of an hundred years, <hi>then had Eſau dominion over his Brother Jacob, as foretold Gen.</hi> 27. c. 40. till this time they were ſeparated from the reſt of the world, under Governours of their own, who deſcended from <hi>Iacob;</hi> and this is the time, when the coming of <hi>Shiloh</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> drew near. And many do here reckon the Accompliſhment of that Prophecy 49. <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. <hi>The Scepter shall not depart from</hi> Judah, <hi>till</hi> Shiloh <hi>come.</hi> But the learned
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Medes,</hi> diatribe in <hi>Gen</hi> 49.10. &amp; <hi>Petavli</hi> Animadv. ad Hzr. 29. Epiphan.</note> Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> hath prov'd that <hi>Shilo,</hi> or the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, <hi>was to come, and the gathering of the Nations</hi> (or Gentiles) <hi>unto him,</hi> was to be accompliſht, before the <hi>Scepter</hi> ſhould finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from <hi>Iudah,</hi> which was not ſo ſoon. <hi>Joſephus</hi> mentions many inſtances of the violence of the <hi>Idumeans</hi> againſt their Brethren in the laſt Civil Wars of the <hi>Iews,</hi> which iſſued in the Final De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De bell. Jud. lib. 4. c. 5, 6.</note> their Temple, City, and Nation, by the <hi>Romans:</hi> when Wrath came upon them to the uttermoſt, and the Scepter departed from <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſo that they have continued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out King or Prince, or diſtinct Government of their own, to this very day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is farther to be obſerv'd concerning <hi>Edom</hi> or the <hi>Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>means,</hi> that they being the old Inveterate <hi>Enemy</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> all the Adverſaries of the Church of God are ſometimes expreſt by that name. We read 83 <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7, 8. in a ſhort Catalogue of the Enemies of the Church, that <hi>Edom</hi> is ſet in the head of them.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106978:6"/>And the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> when deſcribed as a Conqueror over his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, is ſaid to <hi>come from Edom, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.</note> with dyed Garments</hi> (or garments ſtained with Blood) <hi>from Bozra,</hi> the chief City of <hi>Idumea.</hi> As the name of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is uſed for the whole Church of God, ſo the <hi>Edomites</hi> by reaſon of their ancient Malice, and near Neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, are mention'd by a ſynecdoche for all other Adverſaries. On this account we read of ſo many Complaints, and prayers, and imprecations of the Prophets againſt them, and the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek</hi> 25. c 9 and chap 35. <hi>Jer.</hi> 49. c. 17: 18. <hi>Obad</hi> v. 10. <hi>Amos.</hi> 1, c. 11: 12. <hi>Joel.</hi> 3. c. 19: 20.</note> threated by God is anſwerable, in ſeveral places. The <hi>modern</hi> Jews would feign make the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Galatin.</hi> de Arcan. lib. 4. c 28. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xtorf</hi> ſyn: Jud cap. 10. <hi>Schickardi</hi> Jus R. Hebr c. 1. theor. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whom they call <hi>Romans,</hi> to be the <hi>Edom,</hi> that ſhall be deſtroyed, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire they call by the name of the <hi>Edomitical</hi> Empire. The <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> Jews by <hi>Edom,</hi> and <hi>the Remnant of Edom,</hi> underſtood all the reſt of Mankind beſides themſelves, or the <hi>Jewish</hi> Nation, who deſcended from Jacob. The ſpiritual victory of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> over all Nations is thus deſcribed by the Prophet, that his Miniſters <hi>shall lay their hand on Edom and Moab. Iſai.</hi> 11. c. 14. <hi>Moab</hi> is ſometimes taken in this general ſenſe. as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25. c. 10. What we tranſlate <hi>the Remnant,</hi> or Reſidue, of <hi>Edom, Amos.</hi> 9. c. 12. (according to the preſent reading of the Hebrew Text,) the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> more truly renders, <hi>the Reſidue of men. Acts</hi> 15. c. 16, 17. as Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> and <hi>Dr. Pocock</hi> obſerve. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr. Mede's Letter to A. B. Usher. Pocock,</hi> Porta Moſis Miſc. c. 4. in loc.</note> 'Tis there fore-told, that when the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> ſhall be raiſed up in Chriſt, and the Breaches thereof cloſed, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall be taken in, as well as the <hi>Iews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now proceed from this Hiſtorical Account of the <hi>Idumeans.</hi> to conſider what is here ſaid of them, or what is contained in this <hi>Burden of Dumah. He calleth to me out of Seir, ſaying, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, what of the night?</hi> &amp;c. The Prophet is commanded by God, in his viſion, to ſet a Watchman in a Watch-tower, <note place="margin">v. 6.</note> who having related what he had ſeen concerning old <hi>Babylon,</hi> doth now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what he had heard concerning <hi>Dumah,</hi> or <hi>Idumea:</hi> that he heard one call to him out of <hi>Seir,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Watchman, what of the night?</hi> for the better explication of this Queſtion, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it, in the following words, the Original Text (as is <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens de</hi> Qu: <hi>Theol. ſur l'Hiſt. Crit.</hi> lett. 15.</note> neceſſary in other places) muſt be <hi>paraphraſed,</hi> becauſe the ſenſe will not otherwiſe be entire and full, by a <hi>literal</hi> Tranſlation into any other Language.</p>
            <p>One calling to the Watchman out of <hi>Seir,</hi> repreſents the temper
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106978:7"/>of all the reſt; who were ready to ask the ſame queſtion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame Apprehenſions of things, and as deſirous to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd. And this being repreſented in a <hi>Viſion,</hi> the metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe of <hi>Night</hi> is principally to be conſidered, ſignifying a dark ſeaſon of Calamity, Fear and Terror, as the morning light is frequently expreſſive of Joy and Comfort.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queſtion</hi> may be conſidered in <hi>a double ſenſe,</hi> according to the <hi>Principle,</hi> from whence we may ſuppoſe it did proceed: either 1. In <hi>Raillery,</hi> as the effect of a ſcoffing humour, that argued the greatneſs of their Confidence and ſecurity; whereupon they derided the Prophet, and made a mock of the Judgments he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and threatned. Or 2. <hi>As a ſerious Enquiry,</hi> from the real Danger of their caſe, and correſpondent Fears, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In <hi>Raillery,</hi> and ſo the queſtion is ſuppoſed to be put by the <hi>Edomites</hi> to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> or ſome other Prophet of the <hi>Iews,</hi> who had denounced Judgment on <hi>Edom.</hi> (If it be to one of their own Watchmen, that had done the like, it will differ very little.) <hi>Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night?</hi> the doubling of the Expreſſion implies the greater Deriſion and ſcorn, <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <q> You profeſs to be commiſſion'd by God to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee evils to come, and to give warning of approaching Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; you have often threatned us with deſolating Judgments, and told us they were near at hand, even at the door; but where is that <hi>Night</hi> of darkneſs, and diſtreſs you would have frightned us with? whence is it, that we have not long ago been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as you told us we ſhould be? We ſee nothing of the denounced Tribulation and Miſery; we feel nothing of all thoſe diſmal Things you prophecied ſhould come to paſs. Our Sun is not yet ſet: no, we have a Bright and a Proſperous <hi>Day;</hi> and have had ſo ever ſince we caſt off the Yoke of <hi>Iudah.</hi> Or thus. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Watchman, what of the Night?</hi> What Tidings of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do you farther bring us? You have ſaid, it did hang over our heads; Is it now any <hi>nearer</hi> than formerly? What is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all your ſad ſtory of an approaching Night? Where are all the Terrible things you were wont to preſage? <hi>Watchman, what of the Night?</hi> you pretend to be <hi>a Man of God,</hi> who know the times and the ſeaſons, and are favor'd with Viſions and Revelations of things to come; what further Evils do you threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106978:7"/>us with? what is the <hi>next</hi> Miſchief and Calamity, we are to expect? What are we now to look for? Can you tell us any thing more? or is there any thing like to be true, of all that which you have already told us? We have Liberty, Peace, and Plenty for the preſent, and will not be afraid of any tragical Story you can threaten for the future.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this there is a modeſt and ſerious Anſwer in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words; <hi>The Watchman ſaid, The Morning cometh, and alſo the Night. i. e.</hi>
               <q>Tho now you Rejoyce in Proſperity, think your ſelves Happy for the preſent, and are confident and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, with reſpect to the future; as men after a dark and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Night, rejoyce in the light of the Sun; yet your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſhall be made deſolate; Tribulation and diſtreſs ſhall as certainly overtake you, as the <hi>Morning</hi> will be ſucceeded by the <hi>Evening,</hi> or the <hi>Day</hi> by the <hi>Night.</hi> And ſuch a <hi>Night</hi> it ſhall be, as no morning of Deliverance ſhall follow after it. 1 <hi>Mal.</hi> 2, 3. Therefore <hi>if you will Enquire, Enquire; Return, Come: i. e.</hi> if you would know the mind of God, ask ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly about it, and not in an Ironical and ſcornful manner: if you would before it be too late underſtand your Danger, and prevent it; you ought without delay to conſider your caſe, and Enquire <hi>in good Earneſt</hi> what is to be done: and with that Temper and Reſolution, you may <hi>return,</hi> and <hi>come</hi> again, and <hi>Enquire</hi> farther.</q> Or</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe the Queſtion to be <hi>Serious,</hi> from Fear and Terror, on the account of real and apprehended Danger; the <hi>Edomites</hi> are then repreſented, as ſetting a Watchman in an high Tower, to obſerve the motions of an Enemy; &amp; by reaſon of their Fears, they call often to him, to know what he diſcovereth.
<q>
                  <hi>Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night? i. e.</hi> Hath the Enemy attempted any thing farther? doth he approach nearer? in what a poſture doth he ſeem to be? are we in any better, or in a worſe Condition than before? What Time of the Night is it? Is the Morning at hand? When ſhall theſe Clouds be blown over? this night be ended? Is there no proſpect, no approach of Deliverance? ſhall we alway be thus in Fear and Terror?</q> To this the Anſwer is very ſerious and proper, <hi>The Watchman ſaid, the Morning co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and alſo the Night, i. e.</hi>
               <q>You think at the approach
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106978:8"/>of this morning that your Fears will be ſcattered, and the grounds of them removed, and your danger be altogether paſt, and therfore wiſh for the <hi>Morning,</hi> and would fain be inform'd how near it is: But you deceive your ſelves if you think your Calamity will be of ſo ſhort a Continuance, as only for one day: for after the break of day hath put an end to <hi>this Night,</hi> you muſt expect another. If you are not pillag'd, and deſtroyed, and made Deſolate, by this attempt of the Enemy, during the preſent Night, another will quickly come, and your Danger will not be leſs after the preſent cloud is diſperſt. The <hi>Morning</hi> may come, as to a deliverance from preſent fears, but <hi>the Night will</hi> alſo come: tho you get out of <hi>one</hi> Trouble, you will be involved in another; and you will need to <hi>Enquire</hi> again, be as much at a loſs as now, and as ſolicitous to be inform'd of your danger, and to prevent it. Therefore, <hi>if you will Enquire, Enquire,</hi> and <hi>Tarry here with me</hi> (ſo the <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint</hi> expreſs it,) <hi>or abide near me,</hi> and you ſhall know what I can tell you. Or thus, <hi>If you will Enquire, Enquire; i. e.</hi> you may go, and come, and ask again, one Morning after another, and one Night after another; as far as I can diſcern, your Danger is not paſt, or like to be. If therefore you will <hi>Enquire,</hi> do ſo, go and <hi>Return</hi> again, and <hi>come</hi> for Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion another time; as far as I perceive, there will be need of further Inquiries. Your <hi>Fears,</hi> as to the grounds of them, may juſtly Continue: at leaſt, I ſee nothing for my part to the Contrary: if <hi>you</hi> can ſee any thing that hath a better and more favorable Aſpect, we would be glad to hear it; <hi>Return,</hi> and <hi>come,</hi> and tell us. But the moſt take theſe laſt words, as an Exhortation to <hi>Repentance. If you will Enquire,</hi> make ſuch an Enquiry as may be of ſome uſe and advantage. Not only to ſatisfie your Curioſity by the knowledg of your Danger, but ſuch as may aſſiſt you to eſcape it. Let me adviſe you to <hi>ſuch an Enquiry,</hi> as may do you real ſervice. Such queſtions as you put will ſignifie little, if not in order to ſomewhat farther. The great Queſtion ſhould be, How to appeaſe the diſpleaſure of God, and turn away his Wrath; or how to meet him in the way of his Judgments. Therefore <hi>Return</hi> to God by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and <hi>Come,</hi> and joyn your ſelves with his People. <hi>(Tarry with me, or near me)</hi> and try what may be done by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106978:8"/>and Supplication, with Repentance and Amendment, to divert the Effects of his Anger, ſo that the threatned ſtorm may paſs away, and this feared approaching <hi>Night</hi> may not overtake you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Burden of <hi>Dumah</hi> being thus Paraphras'd, and explain'd, let me conſider, 1. From the <hi>Title</hi> of this Prophecy, <hi>The Burden of Dumah,</hi> in what reſpects the threatned Judgments of God (Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Eternal) do anſwer that name of a <hi>Burden.</hi> 2. From the Queſtion, <hi>Watchman, what of the Night?</hi> as in Raillery and Deriſion of the Prophet, conſider the ſin, and folly, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and danger of <hi>Mocking</hi> at the threatned Judgments of God. 3. From the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Night</hi> to the <hi>Day,</hi> in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical ſenſe, <hi>the Morning cometh, and alſo the Night;</hi> Conſider how a Time of Darkneſs and Diſtreſs, a ſeaſon of Calamity and Trouble doth ſucceed, and follow the Peace and Proſperity of the wicked, both as to particular Perſons, and Nations. 4. From this <hi>Queſtion</hi> of the <hi>Edomites,</hi> as <hi>a ſerious Enquiry</hi> (by thoſe who apprehended themſelves and their Country in more than ordinary danger) and the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it, as Containing proper counſel to prevent a threatned Calamity, I ſhall conſider them both with Relation to <hi>English Proteſtants.</hi> 1. That we may take notice, what time of the Night it is with us: or what <hi>ſigns of the Times</hi> may be reflected on, as to the approach of <hi>a Darker Night,</hi> if not ſpeedily prevented. 2. Upon ſuch an Enquiry, what <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning</hi> is our Duty, to divert the Anger of God; What may and ought to be done, to lengthen out our Day of Peace, and render the Light, which yet ſhines, more ſteady and glorious, as well as laſting.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider the <hi>Title</hi> of this Prophecy, <hi>The Burden of Dumah.</hi> The word <hi>[Maſſa]</hi> ſignifies in general any thing that is carried or deliver'd from one to another; and ſo ſtrictly imports no more than a <hi>Meſſage,</hi> or prediction from God, <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Pocock,</hi> comment on <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 1. c. 1.</note> concerning any perſon, or people. It is not alway taken in an ill ſenſe, being prefixt to the promiſe of Bleſſings, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. c. 1. as well as to the threatning of Judgments. But becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> derided the Meſſage of the Prophets, and retorted theſe very words upon them, <hi>The Burden of the Lord,</hi> in contempt and ſcorn; God ſeverely reproves and threatens them for it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. c. 34, 36. <hi>I will punish that man and his houſe, that shall thus ſay, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106978:9"/>of the Lord; Every man's mouth shall be his Burden. Ye have therein perverted the words of the living God: therefore ye shall rather ſay, what hath the Lord anſwered, or what hath he ſpoken.</hi> However, ſince the Predictions and Menaces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity againſt a People, are ſo frequently mention'd under this name, and the Execution of them have the ſame appellative, (<hi>Every man shall bear his own burden, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5.</note> i. e.</hi> ſuffer the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to his ſin,) we may therefore conſider the <hi>Threatnings of Judgment,</hi> as very fitly ſtiled by this name of a <hi>Burden,</hi> with relation, 1. to <hi>God,</hi> who threatens and inflicts Judgment. 2. To his <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who in his Name denounce, and declare his threatned Wrath. 3. To the <hi>People,</hi> againſt whom theſe Judgments are threatned, and upon whom they are Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>God</hi> himſelf. The Judgments which he threatens and inflicts may be term'd <hi>Burdens,</hi> becauſe <hi>he doth not Afflict wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.33.</note> or grieve the Children of men,</hi> much leſs deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Judgment is his <hi>ſtrange work,</hi> and <hi>he cometh out of his Place,</hi> when he cometh to make deſolate. He waits long, and calls often and loud, he gives frequent warning, and doth not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Judgment haſtily, and in a Paſſion; And when the Honour of his Name makes Punishment neceſſary, yet how loath and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing doth he ſeem to be! How backward and Averſe to ſuch a work! <hi>How shall I give thee up,</hi> Ephraim! <hi>How shall I deliver thee, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8, 9.</note> ô Iſrael! How shall I make thee as</hi> Admah! <hi>How shall I ſet thee as</hi> Zeboim! <hi>my Heart is turned within me, my Repentings are kindled together,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <q>Thô thou deſerveſt to be forſaken by my Mercy, which thou haſt abuſed, and ſeized by my Juſtice, which thou haſt provok't; yet how ſhall I find in my Heart to permit it? tho I can hardly tell how to bear with thee any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or without the diſhonour of my Government, delay the Execution of my threatned Anger, yet <hi>Oh Ephraim, my dear ſon!</hi> How ſhall I give thee up? O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> the Poſterity of my ancient Friend <hi>Jacob,</hi> how ſhall I deliver thee over to final ruin, and (as <hi>Admah</hi> and <hi>Zeboim,</hi> that were deſtroyed with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah?</hi>) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> v. 7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. c. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>My Heart is turned within me.</hi> I find ſuch ſtrugglings of kindneſs in my Heart towards thee, that I know not how to forſake thee: when it comes to the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, my Bowels are moved, my affections ſtirr'd, and I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106978:9"/>know not how to do it. <hi>My Repentings are kindled together;</hi> all the thoughts and arguments that might perſwade me to repent of my threatned Judgments, are all muſter'd together to diſſwade me, ſo that I begin to Repent of the Evils I have threatned. <hi>I will not Execute the fierceneſs of mine Anger,</hi> and make a full end of thee.</q> The like in other Places: O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> what ſhall I do unto Thee? <hi>O Judah! what shall I do unto thee? Oh! <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ</hi> 6. c. 4. <hi>Iſei.</hi> 5. c. 4. <hi>Mic.</hi> 5. c. 3, 4, 5.</note> that there were ſuch an Heart in them? Oh that they knew the things of their Peace!</hi> How long doth he wait on a ſinful Nation! how earneſtly doth he ſummon them to Repentance! ſometimes by the voice of his Prophets; <hi>Woing</hi> them by his prophets, who have the Sword of his mouth, 6. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. That they may not be cut off by the ſword of Judgment. And ſometimes in the threatning of Judgment, he <hi>roars like a Lion,</hi> that he may not devour, and tear in pieces. By leſſer ſtrokes of Judgment, he ſometimes gives warning to prevent greater. He firſt makes uſe of a <hi>pruning Hook,</hi> before he takes the <hi>Ax</hi> in hand; he ſpeaks once, yea twice, and a third time, doubling and trebling his calls to Repentance, by the Voice of his Rod, before he gives over a people called by his Name. He ſhoots his arrows of leſſer Judgments, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. c.</note> as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did his to <hi>David,</hi> with Letters round about them; not utterly to deſtroy, but mercifully to inſtruct. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. c. 12, 15.</note> He is firſt as <hi>a Moth to Iſrael, and as rottenneſs to Judah,</hi> before he comes like <hi>a Lion,</hi> and <hi>a Bear,</hi> to deſtroy. The Impenitent <hi>Jews</hi> had leſſer Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>the beginning of ſorrows,</hi> before Wrath came upon them to the uttermoſt. We read of <hi>Golden Vials full of the wrath of God,</hi> 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. <hi>Golden Vials,</hi> becauſe the death of men is precious, and God delights not in it: and <hi>Vials,</hi> ſuch veſſels as no great Evils can come out of at once; coming out thro a narrow neck, they hinder one another, and cannot come out but by degrees; unleſs we break the Vials in pieces by bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der provocations, and haſten deſtructive Judgments on our ſelves. Nay, he doth not preſently deſtroy, tho his <hi>warnings</hi> be ſlighted; but <hi>all the day long,</hi> he is ſaid <hi>to ſpread out his hands to a ſtiff-necked and rebellious People;</hi> thô he might have conſum'd them in the morning, or at noon. He ſets many Beacons on fire, ſhoots off many a warning piece, and gives many an Alarm to awaken us to Repentance. He firſt <hi>whets his ſword,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 7.12.</note> and <hi>bends his bow,</hi> and <hi>makes ready his arrows.</hi> He was but <hi>ſix</hi> days
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106978:10"/>in making the World, but was <hi>ſeven days</hi> in deſtroying one little City, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Josh.</hi> 6.</note> as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> obſerves concerning <hi>Jericho.</hi> He departs gradually, as if he were loath to be gone. He gives orders for their deſtruction, and then recals the Warrant, and tries one year longer. When Juſtice renews her plea, Mercy interpoſeth to beg a reprieve, and pardon. On this account God permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Abraham</hi> to plead with him ſo long on the behalf of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the other Cities of the Plain; If there be but <hi>Fifty,</hi> if there be but <hi>Forty,</hi> if there be but <hi>Thirty,</hi> but <hi>Twenty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. c. 23.</note> but <hi>Ten Righteous Perſons,</hi> for whoſe ſake he ſhould ſpare them, it ſhould be done. God was willing to hear the utmoſt which <hi>Abraham</hi> could urge, to prevent their deſtruction: as if he had told him, that he would have been glad to meet with an Argument, that might diſſwade him from ſo unpleaſing a work. He grants him ſo often, till the Patriarch was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ask further. So unwilling was God to deſtroy; ſuch a <hi>Burden</hi> is the inflicting of Judgment, even to <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tis a <hi>Burden</hi> to the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are imployed to denounce and declare the Judgments of God. How doth the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expreſs his Affection in ſuch a caſe, when he was to threaten Judgment in the name of the Lord, and foreſaw the Execution of it, 22 <hi>Chap.</hi> 4, 5. <hi>Look away from me, I will be bitter in weeping; labour not to comfort me, becauſe of the ſpoiling of the Daughter of my people. For it is a day of Trouble, and of treading down, and of Perplexity by the Lord God of Hoſts, in the valley of Viſion.</hi> So the Prophet <hi>Jeremy.</hi> 4. c. 19. <hi>My Bowels, my Bowels; I am pained at my very heart; my Heart maketh a noiſe in me, I cannot hold my Peace, becauſe thou haſt heard, O my ſoul, the ſound of the Trompet, the alarm of War.</hi> By the ſpirit of Prophecy he knew it was at hand, and as certain, as if he had already heard it. And when the <hi>Iews</hi> ſcoffed at the word of the Lord, and dar'd his vengeance, ſaying, <hi>let it come,</hi> 17. c. 15. How doth he appeal to God, v. 16. <hi>As for me, I have not haſtned from being a Paſtor to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee:</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> as I did not on my own head, without thy call, ſeek the Office of a Prophet to this people, ſo being called, I did not decline to follow thee) <hi>neither have I deſired the woful day, thou knoweſt: that which came out of my Lips was right before
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106978:10"/>thee. i. e.</hi> I was loath to be a Meſſenger of ſuch ſad Tidings, but I have done it in obedience to thee, Lord, thou knoweſt.</p>
            <p>So for <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eternal Iudgments,</hi> threatned by the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of Chriſt to the Impenitent; Tis a <hi>Burden</hi> to their ſouls to conſider the Folly, and fore-ſee the Miſery of hardned, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded ſinners, and declare the woes and curſes in the book of God againſt them.</p>
            <p>But tho <hi>we tell you weeping,</hi> as the Apoſtle, 3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 18. we muſt declare, that <hi>their End will be Deſtruction,</hi> who are Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt by wicked works. You force us to ſpeak terribly, in the name of the Lord. We had rather be Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Peace, than Heralds of War: We would feign be every one a <hi>Barnabas,</hi> Sons of Conſolation; but in faithfulneſs to our truſt from God, and to the ſouls of men, we muſt frequently be <hi>Boanerges</hi>'s, Sons of Thunder: We would rather bring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but glad-tidings of Joy, but 'tis part of our Commiſſion to publiſh the <hi>Severity,</hi> as well as the <hi>Mercy</hi> of God; and <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Terrors of the Lord,</hi> do endeavor to perſwade men, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Corin</hi> 5.11.</note> by that which may work upon their <hi>Fears,</hi> as well as their <hi>Hopes.</hi> We would rather be like <hi>Doves,</hi> to bring an <hi>Olive branch</hi> in our mouths, as a ſymbol of Peace and Reconciliation, than like <hi>Ravens,</hi> to preſage Death, croak Funerals, and foretel deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but Neceſſity is laid upon us, to declare the <hi>whole Counſel</hi> of God; not only, that <hi>whoſoever believes and obeys the Goſpel shall be ſaved;</hi> but that <hi>he who doth not, shall be damned, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 3. c. 16, 18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. c. 26, 31. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. c. 3.</note> he is condemn'd already, and the wrath of God abideth on him;</hi> that there is no <hi>eſcaping, if we neglect ſo great ſalvation: and except you Repent, you shall perish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Burden to the People,</hi> and Perſons, againſt whom <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is either <hi>threatned,</hi> or <hi>inflicted.</hi> Moſt men would have us Prophecy nothing but ſmooth and pleaſant things, and care not to hear of the Terrors of the Lord, of the certain and intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Damnation of the Wicked, who will not turn and live. This is <hi>legal</hi> preaching, ſaith one; this will fright men out of their wits, ſaith another; theſe are <hi>hard ſayings,</hi> who can bear 'em; this is the way to make men run diſtracted, and to drive them to <hi>Diſpair;</hi> and if all this be true, <hi>who shall, who can be ſaved?</hi> Therefore many think, and ſome ſay, of the moſt Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, what the Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> ſaid to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106978:11"/>
               <hi>Icroboam</hi> concerning <hi>Amos, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 9 <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> The land is not able to bear his words.</hi> According to the prediction, that in the latter days, <hi>men shall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſound (and ſearching) Doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3</note> On this account the <hi>men of the Earth,</hi> or Carnal, ſenſual men, are ſaid to <hi>Rejoyce</hi> at the ſilencing and ſlaying of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. c. 10.</note> becauſe <hi>they tormented them with their Words.</hi> But if the threatning, and Denunciation of divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be ſo burdenſom, what will the Execution of them be? If the roaring of the Lion be ſo dreadful, what will it be, when he ſhall devour and tear in pieces? If the menacing <hi>Voice</hi> of God by his Meſſengers be ſo heavy, (when he is ſaid to <hi>Hew</hi> men by his Prophets,) how much heavier will his <hi>Hand</hi> be in the inflicting Judgment? If the meſſage of the Word be inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, which tells you, <hi>you muſt Turn or Dye, Repent or Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish;</hi> if that flash Hell fire in your faces, and you cannot bear it; how much leſs will you be able to bear the Wrath of God, as a Conſuming Fire, when he ſhall make good his word, and fulfil his threatnings? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer</hi> 17 <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>Ames.</hi> 5. c. 18. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. c. 19.</note> They therefore who ſay, <hi>where is the word of the Lord? let it come; who deſire the day of the Lord, and ſay, let him make ſpeed, and haſten his work, that we may ſee it; and let his Counſel draw nigh, that we may know it;</hi> they know not what they ſay; for <hi>the day of the Lord is Darkneſs, and not Light.</hi> They know not what they wiſh; for all his threatnings will prove Terrible <hi>Burdens</hi> when ever they are executed, however now they be deſpiſed, and made light of. Which brings me to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> thing propos'd, viz.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the Queſtion, <hi>Watchman, what of the Night?</hi> as in Raillery and deriſion of the Prophet, to conſider <hi>the Sin, and Folly, and Danger of mocking at the threatned Judgments of God, whether temporal, or Eternal.</hi> I mention both, becauſe the ſame Principle of Infidelity is the ſource of both: and that I may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this diſcourſe the more uſeful to every Reader, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Sin</hi> of Scoffing. The Devil hath tried without ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, by the Rage of Perſecutors, and by the ſubtilty of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and falſe Teachers, to deſtroy Religion, and banish the Fear of God out of the world: but of late he hath attempted the ſame thing by Atheiſts and Sadduces, and Epicurean Deiſts, endeavoring by drollery, and Buffoonry to expoſe the Myſteries of Religion to contempt, and render them ridiculous; deriding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106978:11"/>the Threatnings and Fears of divine Judgment as a groundleſs Bugbear, as only the trade of Miniſters, and the trick of States Men. Such <hi>Scoffers,</hi> 'tis foretold, ſhould ariſe <hi>in the Latter days, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> v. 18.</note> walking after their own luſts.</hi> In other ſins men do not ſo directly ſtrike at God, but ſeek the Satisfaction of ſome luſt or appetite; but in this ſcoffing humour there is an immediate Affront to God, a downright Cotnempt of him, and oppoſition to him: whereas the very Devils own his Being, and tremble at his Power and Vengeance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. However they may ſet up for <hi>Wits,</hi> and think themſelves conſiderable, aſſoon as they are Impudent enough to break a Jeſt upon the H. Scriptures, and deride Religion, yet <hi>this their way is their Folly.</hi> Not only as againſt all the rules of good Manners, to make a mock of that, which the greateſt part of their Neighbors and Acquaintance do reverence, and reckon ſacred; but as they employ their Underſtanding, Fancy, and Wit againſt the God who gave them Reaſon, and a Capacity for Religion, to diſtinguiſh them from Brutes: and as in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to all reaſon, they contradict the faith of all Hiſtory, and the Experience of all Ages; and run againſt the ſetled Judgment and Teſtimony of all wiſe and ſober men, who have inquir'd into theſe things: yea ſome of them againſt their own Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Experience, which they have drown'd by ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and made a ſhift to forget: but the Folly of it will be more apparent, if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Danger</hi> of it: for if there be a <hi>God,</hi> an infinitely Holy, Almighty, and Righteous God, and the Scriptures be his word, they pull down vengeance on their own heads, laugh themſelves into Miſery and Ruin, and ſhall dearly pay for their ſcoffing Humour: let them read 28 <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14, 15, 18. and tremble.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſeldom they eſcape the Righteous Judgment of God in this world; Yea the places where ſuch infect the Air, and the Societies to which they are related, do fare the worſe for them. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. c. 15, 16. <hi>They mocked the Meſſengers of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed his word, 'till the wrath of God roſe againſt his People, and there was no Remedy.</hi> But if in this world they eſcape, the day is haſtning, (and oh how certain, and how near is that day!) when <hi>God will ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi> And when Death and Judgment are in view, will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106978:12"/>they then ſtand to what now they ſcornfully utter in their drunken Mirth? Will you <hi>then</hi> maintain your Slanders? and juſtifie your contempt of God, and his threatned Judgments? will you <hi>then</hi> avouch it as your ſetled opinion, when you are to leave this world? Alas! while you are ſcorning the Judgment of God, and by foolish Jeſts, and Raillery, make a mock of Sin; how many Thouſands are ſuffering under endleſs Deſpair, that threatned ſeverity of God, which you deſpiſe, and ſome of them too did once deride! Will the Holy God, think you, be afraid to fulfil his word, becauſe you make light of it? Will he not laugh at your Calamity, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. c. 25.26.</note> and mock when your Fear cometh? That day is haſtening; for as the <hi>Morning</hi> cometh, ſo alſo the <hi>Night,</hi> which is next to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Night</hi> to the <hi>Day,</hi> that <hi>a Time of Darkneſs and Diſtreſs, a ſeaſon of Calamity and Trouble, shall ſucceed and follow the Preſent Proſperity and Peace of the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will appear to be true, both as to particular Perſons, and Nations. 1. <hi>Particular Perſons</hi> have their <hi>Morning,</hi> their time of Light, and a Day of Gods Patience, to which a <hi>Night</hi> of Darkneſs and Affliction ſucceeds. Let us not be confident and Secure in the midſt of Plenty, Health, and Peace, while the light of God ſhines upon our Tabernacle, and the Evil day ſeems afar off; becauſe Clouds and Darkneſs, Storms and a Tempeſt may overtake us, ere we are aware; and tho they ſhould not, yet the Night will quickly come. And oftentimes when we are moſt ſecure and confident, and pleaſe our ſelves with dreams of a long Continuance of Earthly Bleſſings, ſome great Diſaſter and Calamity, ſome ſurprizing Stroke of Judgment doth ſeiſe us on a ſudden, when we leaſt expect it: The tables may be turned, the ſcene alter, and our Light go out in darkneſs. Let us therefore uſe this World as not abuſing it, knowing that the <hi>Fashion of the World paſſeth away.</hi>
'Tis certain, the cleareſt and moſt proſperous and brighteſt Day of the Wicked, will be followed by an Everlaſting Night. Yet a little while, and their Sun will ſet, and groſs <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> that may be felt, <hi>Vuter,</hi> and <hi>Eternal</hi> Darkneſs, be the Portion of their Cup. If we believe and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee it, let us not envy their preſent <hi>Sun-shine;</hi> for after they have warm'd themſelves a while, with the ſparks of their own kindling, they ſhall lie down in Sorrow. 2. 'Tis true of <hi>Nations</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106978:12"/>and <hi>Countries,</hi> they have their <hi>Morning,</hi> and a <hi>day</hi> of Peace, which is ſucceeded by a <hi>Night</hi> of Judgment and publick Calamity. Thô God had favor'd the <hi>Jews</hi> above all other People, and by a Covenant of Peculiarity they were his Portion and Inheritance; yet there was a Time when it might be ſaid by the Daughters of <hi>Sion,</hi> in the valley of viſion, <hi>Wo be unto us, for the day goeth away,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 6 4.</note> and the shadows of the Evening are ſtretched out.</hi> Their day had many a dark cloud, and violent Storms, when their Country was made Deſolate, and their people carried Captive: and at laſt Deſtruction by the <hi>Romans</hi> put an end to the day of their Peace. And tho more than <hi>ſixteen hundred</hi> years are paſt, their <hi>Night</hi> is not yet ended. The like is fore-told ſhould happen to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church. <hi>All mine Enemies,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>have heard of my Trouble; they are glad that thou haſt done it: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.21.</note> but thou wilt bring on them the Day</hi> of Calamity, <hi>that thou haſt proclaimed, &amp; they shall be like unto me.</hi> They ſhall have their time of darkneſs and diſtreſs, as I have mine. There is <hi>an hour of Temptation</hi> for <hi>Nations,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13. 21 <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.</note> as well as particular Perſons. 'Tis true, God waits long, and gives frequent warning before he doth execute vengeance on a Wicked People; but when they have filled up the meaſure of their ſins, all their Priviledges and prayers ſhall not ſave them. Tho <hi>Noah, Job,</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhould intercede for them, he will not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated. Then ſhall they cry unto the Lord, but he will not hear them, <hi>he will even hide his face from them at that time,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.4. 1 c. 14.</note> as they have behaved themſelves evil in their doings: And all their Auxiliaries and Succors, all their Friends, Confederates, and Allies ſhall prove a <hi>vain</hi> Refuge. Now that we may know how far we and our Brthren are concerned in this, and what uſe we ought to make of ſuch a Reflection, let us</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider this <hi>Queſtion</hi> in the Text, as <hi>a Serious Enquiry,</hi> by thoſe who apprehended themſelves, and their Country, in a more than ordinary Danger, and the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it, as containing proper Counſel and Advice to prevent a threatned ſtorm, that we may be informed, 1. What time of the <hi>Night</hi> it is with us, and reflect upon the ſigns of <hi>a Darker Night</hi> approaching, at leaſt enquire, whether the ſtate of our Caſe be not ſuch as may cauſe us to apprehend and fear it. 2. Upon ſuch an Enquiry, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what <hi>Returning</hi> to God by Repentance, and to love and unity with one Another, is our <hi>preſent Duty,</hi> that if it be not too
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106978:13"/>late, we may yet prevent it. That there are <hi>ſome</hi> Signs of the Times that we not only may, but <hi>ought</hi> to obſerve, cannot be denied; becauſe ſome are <hi>operative</hi> and <hi>Moral,</hi> which have an active influence on the diſmal Events they preſignifie: There are others which are only <hi>Indicative;</hi> and concerning them 'tis more difficult certainly to determin or to make a Judgment by 'em. Altho I am far from preſcribing limits to the Long-ſuffering of God, or pretending to tell, when his Patience will Expire, and bear no longer with the Provocations of <hi>English Proteſtants;</hi> yet, to reflect on the Moral Prognoſtications, and propable fore-runners of National Calamity, can neither be preſumptuous or impertinent, but a ſeaſonable duty; becauſe 'tis by a ſerious obſervation of ſuch things, that God awakens his People to betake themſelves to their <hi>Hiding place,</hi> in obedience to that Call, 26 <hi>Iſai.</hi> 20, 21. <hi>Come my People, enter thou into thy Chambers, and shut thy doors about thee: hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, until the Indignation be over paſt; for behold the Lord cometh out of his place to punish the Inhabitants of the Earth for their Iniquities.</hi> Such things <hi>the wicked, who continue to do wickedly, shall not underſtand; but the wiſe shall underſtand.</hi> 12 <hi>Dan.</hi> 4, 10. And the neglect of obſerving theſe things, is the ſubject of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Complaint and Threatning: that the <hi>ſtork,</hi> and the <hi>Crane,</hi> and the <hi>Swallow</hi> ſhould know their time; but <hi>my People,</hi> ſaith God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 28.5.</note> 
               <hi>know not the Judgment of the Lord. i. e.</hi> They will not obſerve they do not take notice of what I have done, or am about to do in the Earth.</p>
            <p>That the night is not paſt, with reſpect to the <hi>Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> but further Darkneſs to be expected, may be argued in the general, from the flourishing of that <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom,</hi> and Intereſt, whoſe Deſtruction God hath promis'd, and we expect. And who can imagin, that ſuch great things, as God hath foretold, concerning the final Ruin of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhould ever be effected without great Commotions? The laſt ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glings of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to ſupport the throne of the Beaſt, we may preſume, will be the fierceſt. We read of an <hi>Earthquake</hi> to precede the Raiſing of the Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. and of <hi>another</hi> great <hi>Earthquake,</hi> at the Fall of <hi>Babylon.</hi> 16 <hi>ch.</hi> 18. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he, who ſhall be counted worthy to eſcape the things coming on the Earth, and to ſtand before the Son of Man.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106978:13"/>Therefore <hi>he that hath Ears to hear, let him hear,</hi> not only what the ſpirit ſaith to the Churches, but what the Providence of God ſpeaks to the Profeſſors of the Reformed Religion, in <hi>Great Brittain, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> He calls loudly to us, by the <hi>Bonds,</hi> by the <hi>Banishment,</hi> by the <hi>Blood</hi> of our Brethren in other places; (which will be found in the skirts of <hi>Babylon;</hi>) by a Voice out of <hi>Hungary,</hi> a Voice out of <hi>France,</hi> a Voice out of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Fiedmont,</hi> to conſider our Ways, and turn to the Lord; and not to think or ſay, that <hi>they were Greater Sinners than we;</hi> but enquire, whether the cup of Trembling be not like to go round, <hi>Except we Repent.</hi> Some of the grounds of our <hi>Fears,</hi> with reference to an Approaching Night, I ſhall now mention.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tho in the <hi>Evening</hi> time it may be <hi>Light,</hi> yet <hi>the diminution of Heat,</hi> by the declining Sun, betokens <hi>Night</hi> to be at hand. Such is the increaſe of Knowledg among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, the Light is much greater than formerly) that ſome are ready to conclude on that account, that we have nothing to apprehend or fear. But we have no ſuch reaſon to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, conſidering the prevalency and ſpreading of many perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Errors</hi> againſt the Myſteries of Faith; that a Flood of theſe is of late come out of the Mouth of the old ſerpent. If withal we conſider the Prejudices and obſtinacy of the moſt for the Opinions they have blindly receiv'd, againſt the Evidence and Conviction of farther Light. And the miſerable neglect of <hi>Catechiſing</hi> younger perſons, in private and in publick, to the ſhame of <hi>English Proteſtants</hi> in compariſon with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> or <hi>French:</hi> ſo that multitudes have a <hi>Zeal</hi> for the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but not <hi>according to Knowledg;</hi> and by ignorance of the grounds and Principles of Faith and Practice, are prepared for Apoſtacy: and of thoſe who know the <hi>Truth,</hi> the greateſt part hold it in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs;</hi> the Light ſhines in darkneſs, and they have not <hi>received the Truth in the Love of it.</hi> However, granting that there is <hi>more light</hi> than formerly; may it not be the laſt blaze of the Candle of the Lord, gaſping as it were a little flaſh of Light, before it be quite Extinct, and the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick remov'd? Becauſe the Light of Truth is accompanied with little <hi>warmth</hi> of Devotion, little love to God, and fervor in his Service. A ſpirit of Lukewarmneſs, Indifference, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106978:14"/>Formality hath overſpread all Churches, and all Places. And who almoſt is free from the Common Contagion? When the Generality of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> grow Looſe and Vain, Covetous and Worldly, Proud and Senſual, in any particular Country, may we not fear that God will <hi>ſpue them out of his Mouth?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5.</note> when they have loſt their <hi>Firſt Love,</hi> that he will <hi>come quickly</hi> to the like ſeverity againſt them, as againſt the Church of <hi>Epheſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God departs <hi>by degrees</hi> from a People, as he doth from <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons.</hi> Firſt he is caſt out of the <hi>Heart,</hi> then out of the <hi>Cloſet,</hi> ſecret Devotion is neglected; then out of the <hi>Family,</hi> he is not invok't and called upon there; then out of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> publick Ordinances are laid aſide as uſeleſs; and at laſt they are given up to a ſpirit of <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> and <hi>Irreligion.</hi> Any of thoſe degrees have a threatning aſpect as to a further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs. The Tree is firſt <hi>Barren,</hi> and brings forth no <hi>Fruit,</hi> then no <hi>Leaves,</hi> then no <hi>Bark,</hi> and ſo is fit for the <hi>Ax,</hi> and to be caſt into the Fire.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek</hi> 9.</note> So a <hi>gradual</hi> Departure of the Preſence of God from his <hi>Temple</hi> (as repreſented in the Prophet's viſion by five ſeveral removes) threatens further and final forſaking. For as it was not the <hi>Ark</hi> of God <hi>alone,</hi> with the Mercy-ſeat co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Cherubims, but the <hi>Anſwers</hi> given immediately by God in the Holy Place, that were the undoubted evidences of the Preſence of his <hi>Glory</hi> with <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo it is not the Doctrine of the Goſpel alone, and the publick Miniſtry of it, in our days, but the Powerful Operations of the Spirit by the Goſpel on the Conſciences and Lives of men, that is the cleareſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Gracious Preſence. 'Tis true, there is much <hi>Light</hi> by Preaching, but few hard Hearts are melted and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, few blind Eyes open'd, <hi>comparatively</hi> but a few in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The Word is a dead Letter for the moſt part, preacht and heard without the Life, and Heat, and Power of the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. <hi>John</hi> 12.40.</note> Thus it was with the <hi>Jews</hi> before the <hi>Babylonish Captivity;</hi> and ſo in our B. Saviour's time before their final Ruin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When <hi>Drowſineſs,</hi> a ſpirit of <hi>ſlumber</hi> and ſecurity, doth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally obtain; not only among the <hi>Foolish Virgins,</hi> but even thoſe who would be accounted <hi>Wiſe:</hi> When <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are more careleſs and confident than ordinary, ſetled on their lees, little concern'd for any thing but their own Repoſe, and loath to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106978:14"/>be ſtirred up, and kept from ſleeping. 'Tis an ill ſign, when tho their Neighbours Houſe be on Fire, they are no more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with it, than men faſt aſleep on their beds; ſuch a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Judgment doth commonly end in Temporal Plagues: that they who are not ſenſible of the one, may be made to feel the other. For ſuch a provocation, God commands the Prophet, <hi>to ſet the Trumpet to his mouth,</hi> and proclaim war againſt <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.1.</note> Eſpecially when former warnings have been ſlighted, prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Judgments diſregarded, the word of God deſpiſed, his Meſſengers mockt, and his Miniſters ſilenc'd; in ſuch a caſe we read, that <hi>his wrath aroſe againſt them,</hi> and <hi>there was no Remedy.</hi> For this God threatned, <hi>to ſearch Jeruſalem with Candles, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 30.8. 9, 12, 13. <hi>Zoch.</hi> 1.12.</note> and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the men ſetled on their lees: who ſay in their Hearts, The Lord will not do good, neither will he do Evil.</hi> The Security of <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons</hi> is a preſage of their Ruin; when the ſlothful and wicked ſervant thinks his Lord doth delay his coming, he will come, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24.50.</note> and cut him aſunder <hi>in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour that he is not aware of:</hi> when <hi>Agag</hi> ſaid, <hi>the Bitterneſs of death is paſt,</hi> he was neareſt Execution: When the Rich Fool in the Parable, ſaid, <hi>ſoul take thine eaſe;</hi> the next news we hear of him, is that the Pillow is pluckt from under his Head, and he is caſt into Hell. So for <hi>Nations,</hi> in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the <hi>old world,</hi> of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Romish Babylon,</hi> whoſe Plagues ſhall come <hi>ſuddenly</hi> upon her, as <hi>in one day,</hi> when ſhe ſits as a <hi>Queen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7, 8.</note> and thinks ſhe ſhall ſee no Evil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The night is a Time of <hi>Solitarineſs;</hi> men don't meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuch Companies by night as by Day. In the Evening every one ſeeks a Shelter, and an Hiding-place for himſelf to reſt in. Thus a ſelfiſh, narrow, dividing ſpirit generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining among any People, is an ill ſign that a Night of Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is at hand: When <hi>all mind their own things,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4.21.</note> and <hi>few</hi> or none <hi>the things of Chriſt,</hi> or of their common Peace. And here the want of <hi>Concord</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> Diviſions, and Separations, and the ſinful cauſes of 'em, ought to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; eſpecially when they ariſe to that degree, that tho the <hi>Common Intereſt</hi> be at ſtake, men will not, ſo far as in them lies, unite together to preſerve and defend it. I ſhall ſpeak of this more largely in the concluſion of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106978:15"/>
            <p n="4">4. Another ſign of an approaching Night, is when God calls home his <hi>Labourers</hi> from their work, and his <hi>Children</hi> to their bed of Reſt. When his <hi>Remembrancers</hi> in <hi>Sion,</hi> who ſhould ſtand in the breach, to turn away Wrath; they who are the <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>the ſubſtance in the midſt of a Land,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.1, 2. 5 <hi>Jer.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 112.1. 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 2.13.</note> who are the <hi>Stay,</hi> and the <hi>Staff,</hi> the <hi>Chariots</hi> and the <hi>Horſemen</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are called away in great numbers. One <hi>Elisha</hi> by his Intereſt with God, and the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his Prayers, was a better defence to <hi>Iſrael</hi> than Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and Horſes, and all their warlike Preparations. The loſs of ſuch is the weakning of a Country, becauſe they can do more for its preſervation, than the moſt numerous and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd Army. May we not apprehend the fall of an Houſe, when we ſee the principal <hi>Pillars</hi> of it removing. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>The Righteous is an everlaſting Foundation,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon; Fundamentum ſeculi,</hi> as ſome renderit, the foundation of <hi>his Age</hi> and Generation; as if the Happineſs and Peace of any Age depended on the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous who live in it, and when they dye, the Foundations are removed. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65.8. <hi>Obad.</hi> 21.</note> They are the Repairers of Breaches, the Reſtorers of Paths to dwell in, the ſtrength of a People, the Saviours of a Nation. By their Examples, Councels, Authority, Intereſt, and Prayers, they do their utmoſt to ſtop that Current of ſin, which brings Deſolation.</p>
            <p>'Tis for their ſakes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30, 31.</note> that others are not deſtroyed, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional mercies are given, and continued; and deſolating Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments kept off. A Vineyard is watered and fenc't for the ſake of the Vines which bear fruit; otherwiſe it would quickly be laid waſte, and the wild Boar of the Foreſt ſuffer'd to enter. How often had God deſtroyed the <hi>Iſraelites, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 106.23. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.21, 22.</note> had not Moſes, his choſen, ſtood in the breach?</hi> A whole City is ſpared at the Interceſſion of <hi>Lot.</hi> Had there been <hi>ten</hi> Righteous Perſons in <hi>Sodom,</hi> it had been ſpared; and when that number was not found, yet it could not be deſtroyed, till <hi>Lot</hi> was gone. No wonder therefore, when ſuch Interceſſors are removed, if Judgment follow; as when the Wind ceaſeth, the Rain falls. When there are but a few left to ſtir up themſelves to call on God, and know how to wreſtle with him for National mercies, no wonder if <hi>God hides himſelf</hi> from a profeſſing People, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai</hi> 64.7. <hi>Iſai</hi> 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>and conſumes them for their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities;</hi> for ſuch are <hi>taken away from the Evil to come.</hi> While they continue, a ſtorm is often delayed, and Judgment deferr'd;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106978:15"/>as the Wars in <hi>Germany</hi> till after the death of <hi>Luther,</hi> who was wont to ſay, that God would be Propitious, and ſpare 'em as long as he liv'd, and no longer. God will not ſweep a Land with the Beſome of Deſtruction, till the greateſt part of his <hi>Jewels</hi> are pickt out of the Rubbish; and the Reſidue ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken care of. For their ſakes he will ſpare a <hi>Remnant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obad.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.22.</note> and not make an utter Conſumption. And when they can't prevail to divert the Calamity, yet it ſhall be leſſened, and ſhortned for their ſakes. Exemplary Chriſtians, and Faithful Paſtors, are <hi>the Glory of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>ſtars in his Right Hand;</hi> and therefore their Removal cannot but preſage Judgment to follow. Eſpecially when the Ignorance and Corruption of very many of thoſe who ſucceed them, is a new provocation to haſten vengeance. When the nurſeries of Learning are little better than ſchools of Vice; and the ſons of the Prophets ſtrengthen the hands of Evil doers; and the offering of the Lord is made to be abhorr'd among the People, thro the vileneſs of the ſons of <hi>Levi;</hi> for this, ſaith God, I will feed them with <hi>Wormwood,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek</hi> 22.26. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30.</note> and make them drink the Water of <hi>Gall. Shall I not viſit for theſe things? shall I not be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. When the <hi>Shadows</hi> grow <hi>long.</hi> The <hi>higher</hi> the <hi>ſun,</hi> and the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from ſetting, after once he is riſen, the <hi>ſhorter</hi> alway the <hi>shadow;</hi> but the ſhadows lengthen towards ſun-ſet. 'Tis therefore an ill ſign when <hi>shadows</hi> are <hi>greatned,</hi> and ſo much more ado is made about Ceremonies, and circumſtances, and Points of Diſcipline and Church-Government, than for the weightier Things of the Law and Goſpel. When thoſe things, which by one party are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and but a <hi>shadow,</hi> and others fear to be <hi>ſinfull,</hi> are yet impoſed, and urged, as if they were <hi>Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> How deſireable ſoever <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in leſſer things among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may be imagin'd, (as it cannot be proved that the H. Scripture doth require it, ſo) too dear Experience will aſſure us, that it is not practicable without <hi>Perſecution:</hi> And even <hi>that</hi> likewiſe hath been <hi>too long</hi> tried without Succeſs. 'Tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of different degrees of knowledg, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent tempers, educations, &amp;c. will have various apprehenſions about doubtful points. It is not to be expected they ſhould ever agree in the leſſer diſputable Doctrines, and modes of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; nor in any ſuch Terms of Church Communion, as Chriſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106978:16"/>and his Apoſtles have not made neceſſary. But yet they ought, and very well may, bear with one another in thoſe Differences, for the ſake of their Common <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and ſo <hi>hold the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the ſpirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Div. Dialog.</hi> 5. 6. 30. p. 412.</note> "It would confer much to this, ſaith <hi>Dr. H. More,</hi> (who liv'd, and dyed in the Communion of the Church of England,)
<q>if all Opinions and Practices in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that either hinder, or do not promote the <hi>Life of God</hi> in the world, were univerſally undervalued by the Church of God. —and by this means all occaſions of ſquabling, and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the ſhadows and Coverings of Opinions and Forms, being thus removed and taken out of the way, it will be eaſier to perform what the Apoſtle exhorts to, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph</hi> 4 3.</note> 
                  <hi>To keep the unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi> For then there would be no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity or pretence of any ones shewing himſelf to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, but wherin true Religion doth Conſiſt: and no man would be able to buſtle with any credit, unleſs in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of what tends to the good of the People of God, and of all mankind. To this purpoſe he adviſeth, That we all mind the fundamental Myſteries of Truth and Intereſt, appertaining to the Kingdom of God,
<note n="§" place="margin">27. p. 398.</note> in oppoſition to <hi>the Papacy,</hi> which (he ſcruples not to ſay) <hi>is the Kingdom of Antichriſt,</hi> or that City of <hi>Babylon</hi> wherein the People of God were held Captive. We ſhould leave no ſtring or Taſſel, ſaith he, of our Ancient Captivity upon us, ſuch, I mean, as wherby they may take hold on us, and pull us back again into our former Bondage; but look upon our ſelves as abſolutely free from any tie to them, more than in endeavoring their Converſion and Salvation. Which we knowing ſo Experimentally not to be compaſſed by needleſs <hi>ſymbolizings</hi> with them in any thing, I conceive our beſt Policy is ſtudiouſly to imitate'em in nothing; but for all indifferent things, to think rather the worſe of 'em for their uſing them: As no Perſon of Honour would willingly go in the known garb of any lewd and infamous Perſons. Whatſoever we Court them in, they do but turn it to our ſcorn and contempt, and are the more hardned in their own wickedneſs. Wherefore, ſeeing that needleſs ſymbolizing with them does them no good, but hurt, we ſhould account our felves in all things indifferent perfectly free, to pleaſe and ſatisfie, in the moſt univerſal manner we can, thoſe of our own Party — ſupporting our ſelves on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106978:16"/>plain Scripture, and ſolid Reaſon, to uſe and profeſs ſuch things, as will be moſt univerſally agreeable to us all, and do make moſt for the ſafety and welfare of the true Kingdom of Chriſt.</q> Such a Reconciling moderate ſpirit would do much to heal our Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: And if we will not know the way of Peace on eaſier terms, by uniting in the <hi>ſubſtantials</hi> of Religion, God may be provok't to cure our diſſentions about leſſer matters by ſharper methods; to chain us together in a priſon, for the common principles of the Reformed Religion; or ſoder us together with our own blood; as <hi>Queen Mary</hi> ended the differences between the pious Biſhops, <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Hooper,</hi> who in <hi>Edw.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">ths</hi> time could not agree about Ceremonies and Veſtments; The King could hardly get <hi>Hooper</hi> conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> without Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the ſcrupled Ceremonies. But Queen <hi>Mary</hi> compoſed their quarrel, by a priſon and a ſtake. Now they were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reconciled, and wrote affectionate Letters to one another, as the deareſt Brethren: and <hi>Ridley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> ſtoops with his Ceremonies to the others further Reformation, telling him in a Letter when the one was a priſoner at <hi>Oxford,</hi> the other at <hi>London,</hi>
               <q>Now, <hi>my dear Brother,</hi> foraſmuch as we throughly agree in thoſe things which are the grounds, and ſubſtantial points of our Religion; againſt which the world ſo furiouſly rages in theſe days, how ſo ever in time paſt by certain <hi>by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of Religion, your <hi>Wisdom</hi> and my <hi>ſimplicity</hi> have a little jarred; now, I ſay, be aſſured, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fox Martyr:</hi> Dr B. Hiſt. Reform. part. 2 lib. 2. An. 1552 and An. 1555.</note> that even with my <hi>whole</hi> Heart, God is my witneſs, in the bowels of Chriſt, I love you in the <hi>truth,</hi> and for the Truth's ſake, which abideth in us, and I am perſwaded, ſhall by the grace of God, abide in us for ever.</q>
               <q>The ſenſe they had of theſe Differences, ſaith <hi>Dr. Burnet,</hi> ought to inſpire all others with more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thoughts in ſuch matters: It had been happy, if the Fires that conſum'd thoſe Good Men, had put an end to theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts: and if thoſe that have been ſince engaged in the like, will reflect more on the ſenſe they had of them, when they were now preparing for Eternity, than on the heats they were put in concerning them, when perhaps Eaſe and Plenty made their Paſſions keener, they may from thence be reduced to have more moderate thoughts of ſuch matters.</q> Conſidering withal, (as the ſame learned Perſon argues, in his late Excellent <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106978:17"/>concerning Perſecution,)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">To his trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> of the Death of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</note>
               <q>the ſublimity of divine Truth, and what a poor low thing the mind of man is, we ſhall ſee reaſon to blunt a little the Edge of our ſpirits, if they are too ſharp in ſuch matters. — and if Education and Temper, (which prepare men for ſome opinions, and prepoſſeſs them againſt others) have hit together, it will require a very extraordinary elevation to reſcue a manfrom their force. —Among all thoſe that differ, ſome muſt be in the wrong, and thoſe who have the power in their hands, may poſſibly be of the wrong ſide, and in that caſe, all their ſeverity (upon the account of ſuch differences) is turned againſt the Truth, and thoſe who believe it. —Our being ſubject to error ought at leaſt to have this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect upon us, as to keep us from being too ready to judge hardly of thoſe who are of another mind, or to uſe them roughly for it, ſince they may be in the Right, and we may be Miſtaken; at leaſt, they may have very probable Reaſons for their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which if they do not quite juſtifie their Miſtakes, do very much excuſe and leſſen them. —As to the great Controverſy concerning the Obligation which lay on the <hi>Gentiles</hi> for obeying the <hi>Moſaical Law,</hi> tho it were judged by the Apoſtles againſt the <hi>Judaiſers,</hi> yet how gently are they treated, telling them, that the Kingdom of God, or the Goſpel, did not conſiſt in thoſe ſcrupulous diſtinctions of <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> but in <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Joy in the H. Ghoſt;</hi> and that every man was to endeavor to be <hi>fully perſwaded in his own mind,</hi> and was not to <hi>Judge his Brother</hi> in ſuch things, but leave him to the Judgment of God.</q> With much more to the ſame Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Upon ſuch Reflections as theſe, what <hi>Counſel</hi> may be given? as a means to continue the <hi>Light</hi> where it yet ſhines, and render it more ſteady and glorious, (notwithſtanding the threatning Tendency of any Dark cloud) and likewiſe to help what we can to recover it again in thoſe places, where a <hi>Night</hi> of Darkneſs hath overſpread our Brethren? The Directions will principally concern <hi>English Proteſtants,</hi> in ſuch Duties as theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Thankfulneſs to God</hi> for paſt and preſent Mercies, in our own Land, with <hi>Sympathy</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi> towards our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering <hi>Brethren</hi> in other parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> God ſent the Word of Life, the Bleſſed returning Light of the Goſpel to ſhine
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106978:17"/>early upon theſe Nations, by the Doctrine of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> ſcattering the darkneſs of Popiſh Errors, diſcovering the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, freed from the Corruptions and Impoſtures of men, from a Burden of Ceremonies almoſt <hi>Jewish,</hi> and of Superſtitions and Idolatry almoſt <hi>Pagan.</hi> This Light hath been continued by an able and faithful Miniſtry. No Country in the World hath had greater, or on all accounts equal, Advantages with our own in this particular. Forreigners have admir'd the Burning and ſhining Lights in our Candleſtick. And if in any part of <hi>England</hi> there is any defect of this Light, 'tis part of our ſin, and Puniſhment. As <hi>Men,</hi> as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as <hi>English Chriſtians,</hi> our Portion hath been, that of the <hi>Firſtborn,</hi> greater than our Brethren have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed. And tho we have waxed fat, and lifted up the Heel, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the God of our Mercies, and provok't him by our Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; yet with what admirable Patience hath he born with us? By what various methods hath he called us to Repentance? War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us by leſſer ſtrokes, and then turning from the fierceneſs of his Anger? ſaving us for his own Names ſake, when our own Follies, or the Malice of our Popiſh Enemies have brought us within a ſtep of Ruin? How often hath he defeated their Counſels, prevented their Cruelty, and brought their works of Darkneſs to Light? <hi>Many a time and often,</hi> may we ſay with the Church, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 129. <hi>have they afflicted me from my Youth, yet have they not prevailed.</hi> God hath cut in funder the Cords of the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, tied up their hands, broken their Meaſures, bafled their Projects, diſcovered their plots, and cut out other work for'em, ſo that they could not hitherto accompliſh their Enterprize, (and God grant they never may) of Extirpating the Reformed Religion out of theſe Iſlands. What Gratitude do we owe to God, when we Conſtder the many deceived, oppreſſed Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth, that are without Knowledge, Holineſs, or Peace? The vaſt Countries under <hi>Heatheniſm, Infidelity,</hi> or <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery;</hi> While <hi>Brittain</hi> ſtill continues to be <hi>Emanuel</hi>'s Land. Hath any Nation under Heaven been honoured with more ſignal marks of divine Favour? How many and famous have our Deliverances and Salvations been? which all about us obſerve, and ſay, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 126.3.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath done Great things for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the ſame time while we have been ſpared, others have been made Examples to warn us; his Anger hath ſmoakt againſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106978:18"/>his own Inheritance in other places. Our Brethren (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Piedmont</hi>) have been expoſed to the Rage of barbarous Perſecutors; multitudes impriſon'd, tormented, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, innumerable families and almoſt whole Provinces ruin'd, Miniſters baniſht, Temples demoliſht, and a thouſand Out-rages committed againſt the Profeſſors of <hi>the ſame Faith,</hi> that we as yet quietly profeſs and own. Their ſolemn Aſſemblies have mourn'd, and their Blood been mingled with their Sacrifices, while we have had the liberty to worſhip God according to the Rule of the Goſpel, and at the ſame time ſit peaceably under our own Vines and Fig-trees. Their Harps have been hanged on the Willows in <hi>Babylon,</hi> while we might ſing the ſongs of <hi>Sion</hi> in the publick Aſſemblies of his People: and our Country been made a Refuge and a Sanctuary to the <hi>eſcaped Remnant,</hi> who are as Fire-brands pluckt out of the Burning, and in their Exile ſtate have experienced the generous and Chriſtian Charity of <hi>Great Brittain, Holland,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>Shall we not then mingle our <hi>Tears</hi> with the duſt of <hi>Sion?</hi> and put on ſackloth, when ſhe is thus covered with a cloud? Shall we not weep with our Brethren, that weep for the loſs of their Pleaſant things? and feel the Irons entring into their ſouls? Shall we gratifie our Pride, and put on our Ornaments, and indulge our ſelves in Luxury? While they are ſtript naked and afflicted with Baldneſs; while they are fed with the Bread of Adverſity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 22.12, 13, 14.</note> and the Water of Affliction? ſuch ſhall go <hi>Captive</hi> with the Firſt that go Captive, and <hi>this their Iniquity</hi> ſhall not be purged away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Humility</hi> and <hi>Cautionary Fear,</hi> in oppoſition to vain <hi>Confidence</hi> and <hi>Preſumption,</hi> concerning any <hi>particular</hi> Church or Nation.</p>
            <p>Let us not truſt in lying words, ſaying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord;</hi> as if becauſe we have received the Knowledge of the Truth, rejecting the Corruptions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in Doctrine and Worſhip, that no Corruption of Manners could provoke God to puniſh and to deſtroy us. Some build their Confidence of our ſafety on the vaſt Numbers of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> on the ſtrength of the National Church, on the Multitude of thoſe who by common Intereſt are obliged to defend it, and on other ſuch
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106978:18"/>conſiderations for the preſent, or with reference to the future, which may be of ſome weight to a meer Rationaliſt; but if God, upon the Provocation of National Guilt, be riſen out of his Place to execute Judgment, he will reject and ſhame us not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our Confidence, except we Repent. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be apprehended to be the immediate Occaſion of a People's Ruin, in vain do men think to obviate and prevent it without making peace with <hi>God.</hi> And whoever be the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Calamity to a People, 'tis the Juſtice of God, as provok't by ſin, that muſt principally be attended to: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we can be conſident of the ſucceſs of nothing that is attempted for our Preſervation. 'Tis he who in righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment permits an open Enemy to prevail, or ſuffers a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable Miſunderſtanding among them who ſhould Unite: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.14.</note> Tis He who <hi>mingles a perverſe ſpirit</hi> among thoſe who have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold obligations to agree together. If the Voice of Union and Concord among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> cannot be heard, at a time when there are moſt preſſing and importunate Calls to it, <hi>it is of the Lord,</hi> who doth not give an Ear to hear, nor a Heart to conſider.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 12.23, 24.</note> Thus we find it concerning the Diviſion of the Ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the two.</p>
            <p>Some are Confident on other grounds, and expect the ſpeedy accompliſhment of many <hi>Prophecies</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the latter days, and preſume to ſpeak poſitively as to the time. But how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable will be the Diſappointment, if we ſhould conclude for one time, when God hath determin'd another at the diſtance of ſeveral years? How many Holy Men have been miſtaken al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and lived to ſee themſelves Confuted? How different are the Opinions of Learned and Good men concerning the Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Times in the Apocalypſe? as to the Slaying and the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes, and the pouring out of the Vials, whether they have already emptied themſelves upon their proper objects, or when they ſhall; when the 1260 Days of the Woman's Wilderneſs State ſhall expire, and <hi>Babylons</hi> Time and Day be no more, (to determin which we muſt know when it began,) how different are the Opinions of Learned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as to the <hi>Time</hi> of theſe things? Let us not therefore anticipate the Counſels of God, (the viſion being for an appointed Time) by too poſitive Concluſions as to ſuch things; but give him
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106978:19"/>Glory, as the fitteſt Judge of the Times and ſeaſons, wherein to accompliſh his own Great and Holy Purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Neither can we argue from any unfulfilled Prophecies the preſervation of any particular Country, or Church, after great and general provocations, without ſuitable Repentance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. And thô that of all others be the moſt neglected and deſpiſed method of national ſafety, (the moſt think by Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and Numbers, Confederates, and ſuch imaginary Fences to keep off danger) they will yet find, that they cannot more deſpiſe Repentance and Returning to God, than he doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn, and will defeat and ſhame all their wiſe Counſels and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances without it. Therefore the next and principal Duty we are called to is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Humiliation</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of all Parties and Denominations, for their reſpective Guilt, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious endeavors to promote practical Holineſs, and Reformation of Manners. All have contributed to provoke the Anger of God, and more or leſs have been faulty in our carriage to one another; and therefore it becomes us all to ſearch and try our Ways, and turn unto the Lord. God and Men are our Accuſers; we have opened our own ſhame, and it cannot be hid; and the fire is already kindled which reveals our ſin in the effects of it; 'tis no time for any Party or Profeſſion to ſtand upon their Credit, and excuſe themſelves; but rather endeavor to turn away the diſpleaſure of God, by falling at his feet in penitent Confeſſions of ſin, and ſincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>Without this, all other methods will be ineffectual, and the Anger of God will moſt eaſily and certainly bear down before it all the little Banks and Ramparts that humane Policy or ſtrength can oppoſe. It will prove a dangerous and fatal Miſtake for us to imagin by any other means, if this be neglected, to be able to provide for our ſafety. The Folly of the ancient <hi>Gaules</hi> related by <hi>N. Damaſcen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De moribus Gentilium.</note> may move our Compaſſion, who when the ſea broke into their Country, went and ſtood in the breach with their weapons in their hands: and we ſhall be guilty of the ſame or worſe folly, if we think to ſecure the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Religion in <hi>England</hi> againſt a threatning Inundation, by any Humane Expedients whatſoever, without Repentance.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106978:19"/>The uſe of Wiſdom and Prudence is now if ever ſeaſonable; but that <hi>alone</hi> is not to be truſted to: for the Higheſt Wiſdom of any People, under ſuch a Guilt as ours, is to make Peace with God by Humiliation for ſin. Whilſt this <hi>Achan</hi> remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered or indulged, the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be troubled, and we ſhall not be able to ſtand before an Enemy. An Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Cato</hi> (as we are inform'd by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Civitate Dei,</hi> lib. 1. c. 33.</note> who commends the ſaying) could tell the wiſe and warlike <hi>Romans,</hi> that it was impoſſible their Commonwealth ſhould flouriſh, <hi>ſtantibus Maenibus, ruentibus Moribus,</hi> thô their Walls were never ſo firm, if their Manners were degenerate. Our Lives and Converſations muſt proteſt againſt the Corruptions of <hi>Popery,</hi> if ever we keep it out. 'Tis a diſmal ſymptom of an approaching Darkneſs, that ſo few in compariſon are awaken'd to a due ſenſe of this obligation: God's Calls unto it are more loud than ordinary; and we never ſeem'd to be more deaf to ſuch a voice than now. God may juſtly complain of us, as he did of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>I hearkened and heard, but they ſpake not aright: no man Repented him of his Wickedneſs, ſaying, What have I done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This therefore we muſt in good earneſt ſet about, if ever we are eſtabliſhed and ſaved: Every one muſt reflect, and mourn for his own ſins in particular, and then for the ſins of others. There is no party or ſort of men among us who have reaſon to think, that all the ſins, whereby God is provoked, and which are to be confeſs'd and reform'd, are among thoſe who differ from them. I am far from laying the Guilt of National ſins to <hi>any one party</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> becauſe there are no Orders and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of men, no Particular Societies or Parties, in Cities or Country, (however ſome Individuals may have approv'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God) but need a call to Repentance.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the ſins of Profeſſors as ſuch, in Formality, Barrenneſs, Conformity to the World, and decays of Faith, Love, and Zeal, they who have ſuffer'd for their <hi>Non-Conformity,</hi> have been too <hi>Impatient</hi> under their ſufferings; and have ſet themſelves more than they ought againſt the Authors or Inſtruments of them, and endeavor'd to make them odious. Inſtead of looking up to God, and praying for their Repentance, and endeavoring their Conviction in the ſpirit of Meekneſs; by Cenſures and Slanders, Bitterneſs and the workings of Revenge, they have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106978:20"/>fled from Concord, and the way of Peace, and made the Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches wider. What might tend to an Accommodation of our Differences, hath by neither ſide been ſo well entertain'd as it ought. Peacemakers and Reconcilers have been ill treated, and had little ſucceſs. The want of a Publick ſpirit hath alſo been viſible among the ſeveral parties, and is one miſchievous Conſequence of our Diviſions. Every one ſhifting for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a time of Common Danger; taking care of his own Goods and Cabin, with the neglect of what is neceſſary to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the whole Ship from ſinking. There hath likewiſe been great <hi>partiality</hi> in our Eſteem and Affection, towards thoſe of one party, having mens Perſons (for the ſake of their Opinions) too much in Admiration; whilſt others, very deſerving of our Reſpect and Love, have been deſpiſed and undervalued. Neither is there any one Party but hath ſeem'd to ſuppoſe, that the whole Intreſt of Religion was more concerned, than it is, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity or ſufferings of themſelves, and thoſe of their Perſuaſion. I ſpeak theſe things in faithfulneſs to the ſouls of my Brethren, and include my ſelf as Guilty, deſiring forgiveneſs of God, and profeſſing Repentance.</p>
            <p>I likewiſe beg of God, that ſo Conſiderable and Worthy a Body of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as <hi>the Church of England,</hi> may ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the ſeverities they have uſed to their Diſſenting-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to the ſilencing of ſo many Miniſters, (whoſe preaching might be uſeful) to the Ruin offo many Families, and the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of Common <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> by obſtructing the free Progreſs of the Goſpel of Chriſt, the endeavors of all who are qualified to ſerve that deſign, (were the number greater,) being little enough in ſo populous a Kingdom. Beſides the Ignorance, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence, and Scandalous Lives of ſo many of the Clergy, with the Corruption of the Univerſities, Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and Cathedral Worſhip: How hath the Conſcientious Diligence of ſeveral Miniſters been diſcountenanced and cenſured, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectors of the Clergy, for omitting ſome part of the Rubrical Conformity, when ſuch as were manifeſtly ſcandalous have been better treated? In how many places have the more ſerious and Conſcientious <hi>Chriſtians</hi> been reproacht and proſecuted for their Non-Conformity, when Drunkenneſs, Swearing, whoredom, and ſcandalous Immoralities have been overlookt in others, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106978:20"/>the guilty perſons, ſo they kept to the Rites of the Church, been more gently treated, than Diſſenters, thô otherwiſe ſober and unblameable in their Converſations? Such things as theſe we are now called upon, by God and Man, to conſider, and repent of. If all Parties do not ſee their Sin, how can we hope for a Cure?</p>
            <p>If an Apology be needful for ſo much Plainneſs; I ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the Words of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (for whoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Writings I deſire, with many others, to bleſs God,) when he gives the Reaſons of his ſpeaking ſo freely of the Sins of Miniſters, in his <hi>Reformed Paſtor.</hi>
               <q>If thouſands of you, ſaith he, were in a leaking Ship, and thoſe who ſhould pump out the water, and ſtop the Leaks, ſhould be ſporting or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, yea or but favour themſelves in their Labours, to the hazarding of you all, would ye not awake them to their work, and call out upon them to labour as for your lives? and if you uſed ſome Sharpneſs and Importunity with the ſloathful, would you think that man were well in his Wits that ſhould take it ill of you? that ſhould accuſe you of Pride, ſelf-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Unmannerlineſs, to preſume to talk ſo ſawcily to your Fellow-Workmen? or ſhould tell you, that you wrong them by diminiſhing their Reputation? Would you not ſay, <hi>The work muſt be done, or we are all Dead men? Is the ship ready to ſink, and do you talk of Reputation? Or had you rather hazard your ſelves and us, than hear of your Faults?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If after all the Warnings we have had, and the threatning Danger we are in, we will not be perſuaded to Repent, and ſeek the Common Peace; hath not God told us in his Word, and doth he not ſhow us in his Providence, that he hath other ways to humble us than thoſe he hath formerly made uſe of? His Arrows are not all ſpent; he hath a Laſh of Scorpions, if we remain Impenitent under former Rods. <hi>Peſtilence, Sword,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.12, 20. De Gubern. Dei. lib. 7.</note> and <hi>Fire,</hi> have taken their turns, but without ſucceſs. So that the Complaint of <hi>Salvian</hi> is applicable to us, <hi>Nos <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rimur &amp; ſeca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur,</hi> &amp;c. no former Applications have wrought a Cure; and which is more deplorable, we grow worſe by our very Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. We grant this in the General; but at the ſame time our Diviſions have this ill Effect (among many others) that each party is apt to clear themſelves, by laying the whole Burden on the other; whereas all have contributed to the raiſing of the Storm,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106978:21"/>thô few have the ingenuity of <hi>Jonah,</hi> who acknowledg'd, <hi>it was for his ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can we ſay, that our Brethren in <hi>France,</hi> and other places, were <hi>Greater Sinners</hi> than we, whom God hath made to drink ſo deep of the Cup of his indignation? Should we not rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that Our ſin will find us out? and that except we <hi>Repent,</hi> we ſhall alſo periſh? When the <hi>Jews</hi> were in great danger, and as great ſecurity, notwithſtanding the Anger of God againſt their Brethren of the Ten Tribes, they continued to <hi>bleſs themſelves in their Hearts, ſaying, we shall have Peace, we need not fear;</hi> God commanded the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to cry aloud, and lift up his Voice like a Trumpet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nai.</hi> 58.1.</note> to tell the People their Tranſgreſſions: and the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> calleth to the Prieſts and Elders to ſound a Trumpet in <hi>Sion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.</note> to publiſh a ſolemn Aſſembly, to ſanctifie a Faſt, to gather the people, young and old, together, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves, mourn, and weep, to rend the Heart, and not the Garment, to confeſs ſin, and deprecate Judgment, and ſeek the face of God for mercy; and withal, to turn from their Evil wayes; without which no ſolemn Humiliation will be accepted of God, but incenſe him the more.</p>
            <p>Therefore if ever our Breaches be healed, and National De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Judgments prevented, we muſt agree in this, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and Reform, and do our utmoſt to retrieve and promote the Power and Practice of Serious Godlineſs. 'Tis <hi>the Practical Love of the Truth,</hi> with entire Devotedneſs to God, and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious regard to our known Duty, that alone will be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from the Judgments of God, or be an Effectual <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative againſt Popery,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr. Owen, Serm.</hi> 10. <hi>Contin. Morn. Euerc. on</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Ib. Mr. Howe, Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>on Colos.</hi> 2.2.</note> as a late learned Perſon hath proved and preſt it. This has been recommended with great Light and ſtrength by another, who is yet living, in anſwer to that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>What may moſt hopefully be attempted to allay Animoſities among Proteſtants, that our Diviſions do not prove our Ruin?</hi> Where it is proved, that the beſt means to unite, eſtabliſh, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us, both againſt the Judgments of God, and the Endeavors of ſuch as deſign the Ruin of the Common <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Intereſt among us, is to Improve our Faith to greater Clearneſs, Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, and Efficacy, with reſpect to the ſubſtantials of Religion; and to evidence the fruits of ſuch a Faith in holy Love and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Without this, tho we ſpeak and write never ſo much
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106978:21"/>or well in defence of the Reformation, yet whilſt our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries behold our unholy lives, they will ſtill open their mouths to reproach the Reformed Religion, and live in hopes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpating it. In vain is it hop't, that the moſt learned Pens can preſerve the Doctrine of the Reformation, if our Vices contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and undermine its Foundation. Unleſs our manners and Converſation do correſpond to and credit the Religion we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, we are very unlikely to tranſmit its Doctrine to Poſterity, or to keep the poſſeſſion of it our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, To mourn</hi> in ſecret for the <hi>Sins of others:</hi> This ſhould accompany Repentance and ſorrow for our own Sins. The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Abominations for which God threatens to make the Land mourn, ſhould be bewailed; and our <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt them thereby enter'd, that God may not charge us with the Guilt of publick Tranſgreſſions. This muſt needs be <hi>Acceptable</hi> to God, as an Evidence of our Love to him, and of our Concern for his Glory; and <hi>Seaſonable</hi> for us; as a Teſtimony of our affection to that Country and People to which we belong. When the Being of God is boldly queſtion'd; his Providence, and his Authority mockt; his holy name blaſphem'd; his Inſtitutions prophan'd and polluted; his Chriſt (&amp; our Jeſus) vilified and deſpiſed, and by open Impieties crucified again; when his Glory is trampl'd on by abounding Wickedneſs, willful and bare-fac'd, ſo general and to ſuch a degree, as is the uſual Forerunner of Ruin and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; Can we love God, or wiſh well to the Land of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, without mourning for theſe things? Can we conſider the growth of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Infidelity, Popery,</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> and not mourn? Can we ſee <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which God abhors, get ground, and ſo many Thouſands in a neighboring Country receiving the mark of Antichriſt in their Foreheads, and in their righthands, and ſuch a multitude in our own land in a Preparedneſs to do it, and not be affected with the diſhonour of God? not drop a Tear, or lift up a cry to prevent the effects of his juſt Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? And if we love our ſelves, is there any better, any other method to provide for our own Preſervation and ſafety? What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever night of darkneſs and diſtreſs may come upon a Nation, Men of <hi>this Character</hi> have alway been favoured with ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; God hath <hi>ſet a mark</hi> on their foreheads for preſervation, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek</hi> 9.5.</note> when the Deſtroyers have been Commiſſioned to execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106978:22"/>He will cover their heads in the day of Battel, when his Arrows are ſharp in the Hearts of his Enemies. He will hide them in the hollow of his hand, provide a <hi>Zoar,</hi> a <hi>Gath,</hi> a <hi>Pella,</hi> ſome place of Retreat till the Storm be over; give them to find Favour in a ſtrange Land, or overſhadow them in their own, accompany them in Baniſhment, and open the Hearts and Hands of others to ſhow them kindneſs; <hi>Moab</hi> ſhall hide his Out-caſt, and <hi>Cyrus</hi> let go his Captives, and <hi>the Earth help the Woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16.</note> the moſt unlikely means and inſtruments aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and ſuccour that Remnant whom he will ſave. And if we ſhould be called to bear Teſtimony to his Name and Truth by ſuffering for it, ſuch a Temper and Practice will beſt diſpoſe and prepare us for it: It will ſecure his gracious Preſence with us; it will intereſt us in the Promiſe of his Aſſiſtance and Help; and after we have Confeſſed him before men, he will publickly acknowledge and reward us before the whole World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Earneſt <hi>Prayer</hi> to God for the Peace and welfare of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>that part</hi> of it to which we are moſt nearly related. We are required, not to keep ſilence, or give him any Reſt, till he make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> both a peaceable habitation, and a Praiſe in the Earth. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30.</note> When the hand of God is lifted up, there is need of an Enquiry after ſuch Interceſſors as will ſtand in the Gap, and turn away Wrath. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</note> 'Tis time to run with a Cenſer as <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> when the Fire of God is begun to fall down in our ſight; to make haſte, and humble our ſelves, and cry mightily to him, as <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.</note> for the Reſidue of his People, when the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners are gone forth with a Commiſſion to deſtroy; ſaying, <hi>O ſpare thy People!</hi> ſpare the Remnant of thy ſcattered flock! ſpare our Brethren in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Witneſſes of thy Truth! ſpare <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland!</hi> ſpare the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could I repreſent the languiſhing disfigur'd Countenance of the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> mourning in Sackcloth and Aſhes in ſeveral places; whole Countries, which have been as <hi>the Garden of God,</hi> whoſe Inabitants are now as the Generation of his wrath; the great multitude that once walked with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Profeſſion of the Truth, that now walk no more with him; the many neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Vineyards,</hi> from whence a few years ago he had <hi>pleaſant fruit,</hi> now broken down and laid waſt; could I repreſent theſe things fully, you would ſee the Neceſſity of more earneſt Interceſſions
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106978:22"/>with God on the behalf of <hi>Sion</hi> than ordinary. But tho ſhe ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth out her hands, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.2, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Who is there of all her Sons that she hath brought up to comfort her? Who among all her Lovers to pity her? Who among all her Sons to guide her, and take her by the hand?</hi> Even when ſhe is ſhaken, and in danger to have both her Pillars, of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> broken and caſt to the ground? She ſits in the duſt, and few or none ſeem to care for her: and tho they ſee her ſorrow, and hear her complaints, will hardly offer up a prayer more than at other times for her Deliverance.</p>
            <p>However, we have the greateſt Encouragement to make uſe of Prayer in this Caſe of all others, becauſe all the great things promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by God, and expected by his People, muſt come this way. The Return from the <hi>Babylonish Captivity,</hi> tho the time of it was adjuſted in the promiſe, muſt be brought about by prayer. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.10.</note> The wrath of God was poured out on the <hi>Pagan</hi> Perſecutors, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3, 4.</note> in anſwer to Prayer. The Judgements of God againſt the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the Church, come out of the ſame Cenſer, into which the Prayers of the Saints are put. The ſeventh and <hi>laſt Vial,</hi> that ſhall make an end of the Enemies of <hi>Sion,</hi> is to be opened by Prayer. Let our own Caſe, or the condition of our Brethren, ſeem never ſo deſperate, we may obtain Relief this way. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.15, 16, 17.</note> When every Reed, on which we lean'd, is broken; and our fingers knockt off from all humane Dependance; when the ſecular Arm of Help ſhrinks and withers, and nothing but a Wonder can prevent deſpair; when every Prop is remov'd, and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence blaſted; When all our Phyſicians prove of no value; when all Expectations of ſuccor are defeated; when only an Infallible Eye can direct our way, and an Almighty hand preſerve from Ruin; when no Plaiſter will ſtick to our ſore, no balm cure our wound; all our Anchors come home, and our hopes aſhamed; when the Clouds return after the rain; and threaten ſuch a Storm that Affliction ſhall not need to riſe a ſecond time; under the ſmarteſt ſufferings, and deepeſt diſtreſs for the preſent; under the ſaddeſt ſymptoms, and darkeſt proſpect for the future; thô we ſhould hear the ſound as of many Waters, and every thing from day to day have a worſe appearance than formerly, yet by <hi>Prayer</hi> to God we may ſtay and ſupport our ſpirits, both with relation to our ſelves, and the caſe of our Brethren. * Such is the Harmony between the Prayers of the Church and the <hi>Counſels</hi> of God, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106978:23"/>a ſpirit of ſerious fervent ſupplication for <hi>Sion</hi> is a <hi>Token</hi> of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Deliverance. * This ſuccour will be able to reach our Brethren at a <hi>Diſtance,</hi> in other Countries. * This is the moſt <hi>ſpeedy</hi> Aſſiſtance we are able to ſend them, by engaging God for their Help. * This is an <hi>Inviſible</hi> Help, which no Adverſaries can hinder or prevent: Theſe Arrows againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> will kill in the dark, and no force or powre can obſtruct their Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. * This will avail ſometimes when nothing elſe will; ſome Devils will not be diſpoſſeſt, ſome difficulties will not be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſome Dangers not prevented, ſome mercies can not be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, any other way than by Faſting and Prayer. * By this <hi>one Chriſtian,</hi> any one, the pooreſt, the meaneſt upright <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> may help and ſuccour a great Many others, yea the whole Church. This <hi>Every</hi> Good man is capable of, who can do nothing elſe; this Bow and Arrow will fit the weakeſt Arm, wherewith to combate the Adverſaries of <hi>Sion.</hi> * And there is <hi>no caſe</hi> wherein this may not be of <hi>ſome</hi> Advantage; as no other means will be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual if this be neglected. We ſhall obtain ſpiritual Mercies for our own ſouls, as the Reward of it; and it may be a temporal Prefervation for our Perſons and Families: or we may prevail for the deferring of publick Judgments and a longer Time of Tryal; or for the mitigation and leſſening of them; or for a Preparedneſs to meet with God in the way of his Judgments; and the ſanctified Improvement of Publick Calamities; or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain favour for more Innocent Poſterity: And ſhall at leaſt have the Conſolation, of having diſcharged our Duty to our Brethren, and to our Country, and of having manifeſted the Affections of Children, who are ſenſibly affected with the Anger of God, and do what we can to make up the Breach.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore be much in <hi>Prayer</hi> to God for <hi>Sion,</hi> in ſecret, and in Company with others, as we have opportunity: with deep Humiliation and Repentance, with ſincere aims at the Glory of God, and the Honour of Chriſt, with Faith and Confidence, with Fervency and Importunity, with ſtedfaſtneſs and Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: Notwithſtanding the Inefficacy of any former attempts this way, from the ſeeming Delay of God to anſwer; Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that all the ſupplications and Interceſſions of the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God in former Ages will have a real hand, in the final Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Church, and our Prayers muſt help to fill up
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106978:23"/>the meaſure, and <hi>haſten</hi> the Coming of the Son of Man.</p>
            <p>How far the Great Argument, uſed by the Church of old, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.9, 21. See <hi>Mr. Howe's trest. of the Right uſe of that Argum. in prayer from the Name of God</hi> 80. 1682.</note> 
               <hi>We are called by thy name, thou art yet in the midſt of us, and what wilt thou do for thy Great Name?</hi> may be pleaded by us, ought ſeriouſly to be conſidered. For the Caſe of a particular People and Nation may be ſuch, as to give juſt grounds to fear, leſt the Argument from the <hi>Name</hi> of God ſhould make againſt us; leſt the Honour of God, and the Glory of his holy Name be more concern'd to puniſh, than to deliver us. We would humbly Hope, that our Caſe will yet admit the uſe of this Argument, in our Interceſſions with God. <hi>Thou art yet in the midſt of us;</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is Reciprocal between thee and us; and we hope it will be for the honour of thy Name to ſave us. <hi>What wilt thou do for thy Great Name? i. e.</hi> what becomes of us and of our Poſterity after us, is no ſuch great matter; tho we ſhould periſh, and our Name be blotted out from under Heaven: but if the B. Goſpel be removed, or continue to be an Empty ſound, if Prophaneneſs and I dolatry encreaſe and prevail, thy Holy name will be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, thy ſacred Truth reproacht, the Glory of our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ecclipſt, the fruits of his Death obſtructed, and thine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries will triumph, and ſay, that thou haſt born Teſtimony to their Errors and Impieties, favour'd their Deſigns, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanc't their Wickedneſs. Lord! What wilt thou do for thy Great Name? And may we not ſay, that <hi>Thou art yet in the midſt of us?</hi> tho there are not ſo many viſible Tokens of thy <hi>ſpecial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> as formerly, either with Miniſters or People; yet thou doſt walk among thy Golden Candleſticks, and now and then let us know that thy Glory is not quite gone: There are ſome, <hi>(Oh that there were more!)</hi> who feel and live thoſe Truths which others only talk of; who bear the Image of their Lord, and their ſouls cleave to him, and follow hard after him; who delight in his ways, and love his Intereſt and People with a cordial affection, to whom the honour of his Name is incomparably; dear and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious who value his love, and communion with him as their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity; who mourn for the ſins of others, and to whom the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the ſolemn Aſſemblies is a dayly Burden, &amp;c. Oh Continue this Preſence of thine! and vouchſafe more viſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged effects and manifeſtations of it! which we may rather hope for, while he is thus in the midſt of us, than to obtain
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106978:24"/>a Recalling of it, when he is quite gone; as the <hi>Cure</hi> of a Diſeaſe, and the <hi>Recovery</hi> of health may more hopefully be prayed for than a <hi>Reſurrection</hi> from the dead. There is yet another thing very ſeaſonable to be joyned with Prayer, and which we are obliged to, whether we have more or leſs hope concerning any particular Church or Nation; and that is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The Exerciſe of <hi>Faith</hi> in God concerning the <hi>Promiſed Salvation</hi> and <hi>Perpetuity</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi> The Gares of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt her; ſhe ſhall not dye, or Death (whoſe mouth is the Grave) ſhall not be Victorious over her: the <hi>burning Bush</hi> ſhall never be conſum'd. We think this and the other thing makes againſt the Church, and threatens to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it. Here one part is rooted out, there another is oppreſt, and the whole World almoſt wanders after the Beaſt, and the Falſe Prophet. <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Amaleck,</hi> and <hi>Moah</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> are all in a confederacy and Combination againſt <hi>Sion.</hi> But if it were yet worſe, we muſt live by <hi>Faith,</hi> that all ſhall tend to the accompliſhment of God's great deſign, of the Furtherance of the Goſpel: The truly Chriſtian Intereſt ſhall live, and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and get ground after all oppoſition; yea by thoſe thins ſhall it be advanc't,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13.</note> which we may apprehend as prejudicial to it. <hi>God's thoughts are not as ours,</hi> nor his ways as ours; what we think a threatning miſchief, may prove a great Bleſſing, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doth ſo. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.7.</note> What a Compaſs did Iſrael fetch from <hi>Aegypt</hi> to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and yet God ſaith, he led them by <hi>the Right way?</hi> forty years in a journey, that might have been deſpatcht in ten days. He is never out of his way, or miſtaken in the methods of his Providence to fulfil his word. This we are moſt certain of, that the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Chriſtian Church ſhall live in the midſt of all ſtorms, be rooted and eſtabliſht by the moſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Providences: and that when it ſeems <hi>loweſt,</hi> and moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſink, it is the fitteſt time for the Wiſdom, Power, and Faithfulneſs of God to diſcover it ſelf. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev</hi> 5.4.</note> When none was found worthy or able to open the book, the <hi>Lamb</hi> takes it out of the hands of him who ſat on the throne. Our Exalted Saviour, who hath the Keys of Death and Hell, is not weary of holding the Scepter in his hand. He ſits at Helm, and ſteers the ſhip, and will not ſuffer it to periſh. Therefore no Depths, no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, no delay of deliverance, ſhould diſhearten us. If God
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106978:24"/>will work, <hi>a Fire not blown</hi> shall conſume his Enemies, and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> ſhall come together. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 20.26, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>The Viſion is for an appointed Time,</hi> in the end it ſhall ſpeak, it ſhall not Lye; <hi>it shall Come, it will not Tarry:</hi> tho to our <hi>Senſe</hi> it may ſeem to Tarry, our <hi>Faith</hi> muſt correct the Verdict of our Senſe, and make us wait for it: for not a word or tittle of what God hath ſpoken concerning the latter days ſhall be unfulfilled.</p>
            <p>When Providences are dark, and a ſtorm is begun, we are ready to be puzzled, and cry out; <hi>what shall we ſay to theſe things?</hi> but let us remember what the Apoſtle adds, as a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reply, <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.</note> we are apt to queſtion the <hi>Power</hi> of God: this is at the bottom of our unbelieving Fears; were it otherwiſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Numb.</hi> 11.19, 21.</note> we ſhould not believe and truſt God leaſt, when Dangers are greateſt. When <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's</hi> faith had overcome that Difficulty about the Power of God, he was able to triumph over all diſcouragements. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.17: 18, 19.</note> God can do more abundantly for us than we can ask or think; and give Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal Salvation at once; that upon <hi>Mount Sion</hi> there ſhall be <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> too. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obad.</hi> 47.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let us not then be diſcouraged: God rules over all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Earth, and changeth the Government, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of them as he pleaſeth. He hath toſſed up and down the Powers of the world by turns: and can and will do the like again, as ſhall beſt ſerve the ends of his Glory, and the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his word. Sometimes almoſt all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> have been <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and on a ſudden the ſcene hath changed, and the moſt of them have given their Power to the Beaſt. In one year, <note place="margin">Anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti 1619. <hi>See Rush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths: Collect:</hi> 17: <hi>Jacobi</hi> 1.</note> when in <hi>Holland</hi> the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> was called, the King of <hi>England</hi> was a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and the Prince <hi>Elector Palatine,</hi> a Proteſtant, was choſen King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five</hi> Princes in <hi>Germany</hi> were alſo <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> inſomuch that ſome were ready to cry out, the <hi>Golden Age</hi> was come, and the <hi>Glory</hi> of the latter Times. But within <hi>one year,</hi> all was turned again: when the <hi>Bohemians</hi> were routed, and their new King and Queen forced to fly into <hi>Holland,</hi> being over-thrown by the <hi>Imperial</hi> Forces, in the famous Battel at <hi>Prague.</hi> Upon which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Union in <hi>Germany</hi> declin'd, and moſt of the Princes of it reconciled themſelves to the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and only interceded for the <hi>Palatine,</hi> but in vain. We muſt truſt in God, and live by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106978:25"/>
               <hi>faith,</hi> notwithſtanding all the changes and revolutions of the world; tho the <hi>Kings</hi> of the Earth ſhould not be <hi>Nurſing Fathers</hi> to the Church, as well as when they are.</p>
            <p>The laſt Counſel is <hi>mutual Forgiveneſs,</hi> and <hi>Forbearance,</hi> with ſerious endeavors, in our ſeveral Places after <hi>Chriſtian Concord.</hi> And becauſe of the ſeaſonableneſs of this advice to <hi>English Proteſtants,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak of it under ſeveral Conſiderations, which may enforce the duty, and aſſiſt us in the performance of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider the <hi>Common obligations</hi> we are all under, <hi>as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> to <hi>Brotherly Love,</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> and to endeavor the Unity and <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> Theſe things were never diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any, and therefore it will not be needful to ſay much in the Praiſe of them: as that <hi>Love</hi> is the fulfilling of the Law, the End of Faith, the badge of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> &amp;c. that all Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Gifts, Utterance, Sufferings are in vain, where this is wanting. But 'tis Ignorance and miſtake concerning the nature of Brotherly Love and Union, and of the way and means that lead to it, that hath made our Diviſions and the Conſequences of them ſo miſchievous to the Church of God. For the Unity of the Church in Faith and Love may very well be preſerved, without having juſt the ſame Conceptions of all Revealed Objects. Such an Union as that is morally impoſſible, and can never be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; and therefore to endeavor the Peace of the Church on that Foundation, is an hopeleſs and vain attempt. As much may be ſaid concerning an Union in doubtful, unſcriptural Rites, Orders, and Ceremonies: None of our Lords commands of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or directions for it, do either require, or ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this. Many leſſer Differences in opinion and practice are conſiſtent with the nature, ends, and fruit of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and enjoyned by the Goſpel; if ſuch differences be but manag'd with a ſpirit of love, mutual Forbearance, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention.</p>
            <p>Our great care muſt be to Remember our Relation to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riverſal Church</hi> of Chriſt upon Earth, which is <hi>firſt</hi> in order of nature, by our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> before our Relation to any <hi>particular</hi> Church; and is both more noble, more neceſſary, and more Durable. We muſt therefore take heed of confining our Love to any one Party of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> becauſe of our mind and way, (altogether as unreaſonable as to love only thoſe of our own Age,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106978:25"/>Stature, or Complexion,) leſt the great and more comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Intereſt of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Proveſtants,</hi> be forgotten and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: leſt a narrow Zeal for a ſmall Party of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould prejudice the Intereſt of the Univerſal Church, or cauſe of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> There is <hi>one God,</hi> and one Lord, <hi>one Head,</hi> and <hi>one Saviour,</hi> into whoſe name we are all Baptized; <hi>one Covenant,</hi> which all in Baptiſm make with this one God and Saviour; <hi>One ſpirit,</hi> whereby we are all Regenerated; one <hi>New Creature,</hi> in all Holy <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> begotten by this Spirit; <hi>One Goſpel,</hi> the Rule of Faith and Life, and Foundation of our Common Hope; <hi>one Body</hi> of Chriſt, both <hi>Myſtical</hi> and <hi>Viſible;</hi> (all real <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> are members of the former, and all profeſſing <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of the latter, by viſible ſubjection to Chriſt as their Head;) <hi>one way</hi> of Faith and Holineſs, wherein all muſt walk; <hi>one End,</hi> and <hi>Happineſs;</hi> which all expect; and <hi>one Heaven,</hi> where all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God ſhall meet, and live forever, (however they fall out by the way) with one mind and Heart, in one Bleſſed work of Praiſing our Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier. From hence cannot but reſult an obligation to Brotherly love and Unity in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Peace and Proſperity of the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church; not reproaching others as Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, who are not of our mind in leſſer things; not partially excuſing the faults of them who are, and aggravating thoſe of other <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and Brethren, whoſe ſalvation we ſhould deſire and endeavor, and not lay ſnares before 'em, much leſs hate and perſecute 'em, becauſe in ſome things they do not think, and ſpeak, and act as we do. How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming is it the Diſciples of the Prince of Peace (his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters eſpecially) to render the greateſt part of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> odious, and tempt the weak to Slanders, Judgings, and Envies, which are fruits of the Fleſh?</p>
            <p>If ever God will Heal his Broken Churches, a ſpirit of Love, and Unity, and moderation muſt be reviv'd, inſtead of fierce dividing zeal: and the H. Scriptures alone be thought a ſufficient Rule; and no mens Confeſſions made the Teſt of Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion any farther than as plainly agreeing with the H. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Concord and Union upon ſuch terms in which we are all agreed, muſt be our Cure, if ever we are cured. But Healing Truths are never likely to be entertain'd among us till God give healing ſpirits to the Paſtors, and Leaders of the Church. The
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106978:26"/>Conceſſions of the moderate men of all Parties, would be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient foundation for Agreement, (in Chriſtian love to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for the Intereſt of the whole; managing the leſſer diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences with mutual forbearance and condeſcention, without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering or troubling the Church. Loving thoſe with whom we cannot in all particulars joyn, correſponding with them in what we can, praying for and with them, Treating them as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſubjects of the Kingdom of Chriſt, pittying them in their Afflictions, Sufferings, Errors, and Temptations, relieving their wants as we are able, having no averſation to their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not ſeeking their Hurt, or rejoycing in it, not judging or cenſuring them, (any otherwiſe than natural Reaſon, and the Rule of Scripture will allow) much leſs rejecting them from the Body of Chriſt, by unchurching of 'em.</p>
            <p>They who are thought to go fartheſt from the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Diſcipline, while they all acknowledg the Doctrine of the 39 Articles, however they may be accuſed, have declared their Moderation, as to their Brethren from whom they differ, in as full and charitable Expreſſions, as can well be deſired;
<q> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Phil. Nye</hi> hath wrotea book to prove the lawfulneſs of hearing the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and before him <hi>Ames</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Treatiſe of Evang. Love and Unity. p. 85, 86.</note> God forbid, ſaith D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Owen,</hi> that any ſuch thought ſhould enter into our Hearts, as tho the Churches conſtituted in all things according to our light, and the rules we apprehend apointed in Scripture for that purpoſe, ſhould be the only true Churches in the World; and whilſt we judge others to be <hi>true</hi> Churches, we ſhall not be much moved or provokt by their Judgment, who think ours are none, becauſe we differ from them, and plead for Reformation beyond their meaſure. We have the ſame thoughts of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches in <hi>Europe,</hi> called <hi>Reformed,</hi> the ſame love towards them, the ſame readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Communion with them, as we would deſire any Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt in the World to have, bear, or exerciſe towards us. We do not think that the things wherein they fail, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they miſs, or out-go the rule, are in their own nature ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely deſtructive of their Church State.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Experience, one would think, ſhould now call us to mutual forbearing one Another in Love. And whatever be the Reward of Reconcilers from men, (commonly to be ill thought and ſpoken of by many of the differing parties) yet he that calleth to Love and union, calls to <hi>Holineſs.</hi> All that is againſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106978:26"/>
               <hi>Love,</hi> is againſt Holineſs, againſt God, againſt Chriſt, againſt his Spirit, his Church, and the Intereſt of Mankind. The want of forbearing one another in Love hath brought us more than once very near to Ruin. And how long, and how often have we been warned of this! <note place="margin">Preface to his Intereſt of England.</note> The pious and Judicious M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Corbet</hi> told our Brethren thirty years ago,
<q>That they who contemned. All Overtures of Peace, Union, and Accommodation, might come to ſee the need, and know the want of it, as well as others; for who knoweth (ſaid he) what God is doing, or where will be the end of his working, whoſe Judgments are unſearchable and paſt our finding out?</q> And how often hath the Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Baxter</hi> told the world, to the diſpleaſing ſome of all Parties, that what Party ſoever it be that endeavors a Union, by the Extirpation and Ruin of the other part, whether <hi>Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, Independent,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> is Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trcal, and takes the way of Deſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider the impoſſibility of our agreement in things <hi>Dark, Doubtful,</hi> and <hi>Numerous;</hi> and the unreaſonableneſs of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring it by ways of <hi>Violence.</hi> The terms of <hi>Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> laid down by the Apoſtle, 4 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. are ſew and ſure, plain and poſſible. And after all the methods that have been tried by any, to bring us to unite upon other terms, than thoſe of the Scripture; we ſee they are as far from effecting it as ever. Every one muſt endeavour to be fully perſuaded in his own mind, as to what he is to believe and practiſe in things ſacred and Religious; nor may he make his own underſtanding the Rule of Truth and Worſhip unto others. Every Conſcientious man ought to be determin'd by his own reaſon and Judgment, regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the word of God, concerning his duty, as to the Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Soul. For men to adhere to any particular Church, or to refuſe communion with any, when opportunity offers, on any other account, than becauſe they think it their <hi>Duty</hi> to do ſo, is neither becoming Men, or <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And they wo are Conſcious of their own Sincerity herein, will be moſt inclin'd to judge favourably of Others, who differ from them, and to hope that they alſo Act ſincerely upon the like Principle, according to their Light. And will likewiſe be carefull how they faſten ill and odious <hi>Conſequences</hi> upon thoſe different Opinions which Others hold, if they be ſuch as they diſown, and would deteſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106978:27"/>the Doctrines, if they were convinc't that any ſuch Conſequences did belong to them.</p>
            <p>After all that can be ſaid or done to juſtifie the Severities, which any have uſed in ſuch Caſes towards their Brethren, (I exclude none who have at any time been guilty,) the greateſt part of <hi>Sober men</hi> will ſtill believe, that all <hi>Power</hi> from God to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes and Paſtors, is for Edification, and not for Deſtruction: that he never gave any againſt his own Laws, and the Intereſt of the ſouls of men. They will ſtill think, that they are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, it ſhould be, for the wellfare of their own ſouls; and can beſt tell what they find to be profitable or hurtful to 'em, and moſt for their edification; and that if no Humane Authority can tye up a man to eat that which he cannot digeſt, ſo neither to attend that Miniſtry only, which they do not find ſo much to the Advantage and Edification of their ſouls, as ſome other which God affords them. The different <hi>Relishes</hi> of the minds of men may here be conſidered, and the benefit of gratifying them in order to edification. For I know of ſome, and hear of many, who profeſs that they are never more Reverent, devout, and ſerious, and their Hearts more affected, than in the uſe of the <hi>Common Prayer:</hi> others profeſs with the like ſeriouſneſs, as to themſelves, that they Experience the Contrary. And ſhall we think it reaſonable, that they ſhould be obliged to the meaſures of the former? or that either ſhould cenſure the other, as not belonging to Chriſt on that account? Is there any Law of Chriſt, any Rule of the Goſpel, any duty of Love to the Brethren, that can require men to hinder their Edification? or to joyn in ordinary local Communion there, where they cannot attain the great ends of Church Communion? Nevertheleſs, we muſt be Careful not to <hi>have the Faith of our Lord I. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>James</hi> 2.1.</note> Chriſt with reſpect of Perſons.</hi> For there is a culpable Partiality with reſpect to Miniſters, cauſing Envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.4.</note> Diviſions, and Strifes, which the Apoſtle condemn'd in the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were Miniſters humble and ſelf-denying, and did we more Earneſtly deſire and ſeek the Honour of God, the Advancement of Holineſs, and the ſalvation of ſouls, we ſhould rejoyce if the people could learn more, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr. Baxter</hi> Cure of Ch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iv. dir. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Min.</note> and edifie better by other mens Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry than our own; tho it may be ſome error in Judgment that directed their choice. A true Mother who knows her Child is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106978:27"/>like to thrive more by the milk of another woman than her own, will be ſo far from hatred or envy at the Nurſe or Child, that ſhe will conſent, and be glad of it. Would a faithful Phyſitian rather let his Patient pine away in a Conſumption, than be healed by another, whom the Patient (with, or without cauſe) prefers before him? I know there needs a great deal of <hi>ſelf-denial</hi> unto this but I think it ought to be ſo, becauſe the Apoſtle rejoyced <hi>that Chriſt was preacht,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15, 16, 18.</note> tho by them who did it in <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Envy,</hi> to add affliction to his bonds.</p>
            <p>If any number of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> judge, tho it ſhould be by miſtake, that the terms of Church Communion required of them are <hi>ſinful,</hi> (and of doubtful and numerous ones very many are like to think ſo) can they act like Honeſt men to comply while they thus judge?</p>
            <p>Will any be ſo unreaſonable, as to deſire me to do that to pleaſe him, (and puniſh me if I will not) when I apprehend I ſhould diſpleaſe God by doing it? Is it at all ſtrange, that many ſerious <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in a Country Pariſh, cannot content themſelves with ſuch Guides of their ſouls, as an Ignorant, drunken Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron ſhall think fit to put over them, who it may be are as bad as he? What if they think they have a natural Right to chooſe one themſelves? As well as to chooſe their Phyſitian, or Lawyer, and rather, as the Conſequence is more, and greater? eſpecially ſince ſuch a Principle is allowed by Leading men in the Church of England.
<q>For every man to Worſhip God according to his Conviction, <note place="margin">Preface con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</note> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi>) is <hi>an eſſential Right of Humane nature,</hi> Antecedent to all humane Government, and can never become ſubject to it.</q> What the Rev. <hi>Dean of S. Pauls</hi> (whoſe ſingular Learning is ſo deſervedly honoured in all the Reformed Churches,) hath diſcourſt formerly on this ſubject, cannot be too often tranſcrib'd, viz, in the peaceable and Chriſtian Preface to his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> and in the
<note n="*" place="margin">Part. 1. c. 6 p. 118— 123.</note> book it ſelf, <hi>If he continue not in every thing of the ſame mind, Truth and Reaſon is ſtill the ſame.</hi> And D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Sherlock</hi> tells the A. B. of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the Epiſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory to his Anſwer to the <hi>Firſt part</hi> of <hi>The Proteſtant Reconciler, That a Recantation of a Book is no Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let me add, that the Chriſtian Deſign of that book, the Firſt part of the <hi>Prot. Reconciler,</hi> and the Judgment and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Worthy Author, it is hoped will now be otherwiſe eſteem'd of, than three or four years ago, when ſo Great a man
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106978:28"/>as <hi>the Maſter of the Temple</hi> treated both with ſo much ſharpneſs and contempt.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Laws of Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Dr. St.</hi> were meek and gentle; the Duties he required were neceſſary, juſt and reaſonable. He that came to take away the inſupportable yoke of Jewiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, certainly did never intend to gall the necks of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, with <hi>another</hi> inſtead of it: and it would be ſtrange the Church ſhould require <hi>more</hi> than Chriſt himſelf did, and make <hi>other</hi> Conditions of Communion, than our Saviour did of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipleſhip. What poſſible reaſon can be given, why ſuch things ſhould not be <hi>ſufficient for Communion</hi> with a Church, that are ſufficient for Eternal ſalvation? and certainly thoſe things are ſufficient for that, which are laid down as the <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> duties of Chriſtianity by our Lord and ſaviour in his word. What ground is there why Chriſtians ſhould not ſtand on the <hi>ſame terms</hi> now, which they did in the time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> was not Religion <hi>ſufficiently</hi> guarded and fenced in them? was there ever more true and Cordial <hi>Reverence</hi> in the Worſhip of God? What Charter hath Chriſt ever given the Church, to bind up men to <hi>more</hi> than himſelf hath done? and to exclude thoſe from her Society, who may be admitted into Heaven? — The grand Commiſſion the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were ſent out with, was only <hi>to teach what Chriſt had commanded them,</hi> not the leaſt intimation of any power given them to impoſe, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any thing beyond what he himſelf had ſpoken to them, or they were directed to by the immediate guidance of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. — We never read the Apoſtles making Laws but of things ſuppoſed neceſſary. When the Council of the <hi>Apoſtles met</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for deciding a Caſe that diſturbed the Churches peace; we ſee they would lay <hi>no other Burden</hi> on the Gentile Chriſtians <hi>beſides thoſe Neceſsary things.</hi> 15. Act. 29. It was not enough with them that the things would be neceſſary when they had requir'd them, but they lookt on an <hi>Antecedent Neceſſity,</hi> either abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, or for the preſent State, which was the only ground of their impoſing thoſe Commands. There were after this great <hi>Diverſities</hi> of Practice, and <hi>varieties</hi> of obſervations among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; but the H. Ghoſt never thought thoſe things fit to be made matters of <hi>Laws,</hi> to which all Parties ſhould Conform; all that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> required as to theſe, was <hi>mutual forbearance</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106978:28"/>and condeſcention towards each other in them. The Apoſtles valued not <hi>Indifferences</hi> at all; and thoſe things 'tis evident they accounted <hi>ſuch,</hi> which whether men did them or not was not of Concernment to Salvation. And what Reaſon is there, why men ſhould be ſo ſtrictly tied up to <hi>ſuch things,</hi> which they may do, or let alone, and yet be <hi>very good Chriſtians</hi> ſtill? Without all Controverſie (ſaith the <hi>Doctor,</hi> and <hi>Experience will</hi> confirm it,) the main in-let of all the <hi>Diſtractions, Confuſions,</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions</hi> of the Chriſtian World, hath been by adding <hi>other Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of Church Communion than Chriſt hath done. Would there ever be leſs <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the Church, if a <hi>Diverſity</hi> were allowed as to Practices ſuppoſed indifferent? yea, there would be ſo much more, if there were a mutual forbearance and Condeſcention as to ſuch things. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Church is an unity of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> and not a bare <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> of Practice and Opinion. — Were we but ſo Happy, as to take off things granted unneceſſary by all, and ſuſpected by many, and judged unlawful by ſome, and to make nothing the bonds of our Communion but what Chriſt hath done, <hi>one Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. allowing a <hi>Liberty</hi> for matters of Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, and bearing with the Weakneſs of thoſe who cannot bear things which others count lawful, we might indeed be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to a true <hi>primitive</hi> Luſtre, far ſooner than by ſurbiſhing up ſome antiquated Ceremonies, that can derive their pedigree no higher than ſome <hi>Ancient</hi> Cuſtom and Tradition. <hi>God will one day convince men, that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Church lyes more in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Faith, and Affection, than in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of doubtful Rites and Ceremonies.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And after that unſeaſonable Sermon at <hi>Guildhall</hi> of the <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of Separation,</hi> yet in the Defence of it, <note place="margin">P. 81, 82.</note> the D<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face propounds this very ſeaſonable Queſtion
<q>
                  <hi>What then? Is there nothing to be done for diſſenting Proteſtants, who agree with us in all doctrinal Articles of our Church, and only ſcruple the uſe of a few Ceremonies, and ſome late Impoſitions? Shall theſe Differences ſtill be Continued, when they may ſo eaſity be removed? And ſo many uſeful men encouraged, and taken into the Conſtitution? Do we value a few Indifferent Ceremonies, and ſome late Declarations, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Expreſſions, beyond the Satisfaction of mens Conſciences, and the Peace and Tranquility of the Church?</hi> In Anſwer, he ſaith, That
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106978:29"/>tho he thinks there is no ground for ſcruple as to the uſe of thoſe things, Notwithſtanding that, <hi>becauſe the uſe of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a Chriſtian Church ought to be the moſt free from all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, and they ought to be ſo adminiſtred as to invite, rather than diſcourage Scrupulous perſons from joyning in them; I do think it would be a part of Chriſtian Wiſdom and Condeſcention in the Governours of our Church, to remove thoſe bars from a freedom in joyning in full Communion with us.</hi>—</q> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider the great <hi>Miſchief</hi> of our paſt and preſent <hi>Diviſions,</hi> to the Intereſt of Real Chriſtianity, the Reformed Religion, and the Peace and Happineſs of the Nation. The Contentions among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the paſſionate Heats among <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> themſelves, and the ſeverities uſed by others to enforce an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> have diſhonoured the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, and coſt the Nation very dear on all accounts. Theſe things have hindred the uſefulneſs and fruit of many Miniſters preaching, and depriv'd us of the advantage of the publick labours of many hundred others, and leſſen'd the Authority and Succeſs of the Miniſtry in general, filling many with ſuch prejudices, that they have turned their backs upon all preaching. By this means the weak have been ſcandaliz'd, <note place="margin">See <hi>Firſt Part of the Prot. Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiler.</hi> chap. 1. Mr. <hi>I. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> Ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum chap. 27, 28, 29, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the doubtful ſtaggered, Infidels hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Scepticks gratified, Popery and Prophaneſs advanc't, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſouls endanger'd, the Devil pleaſed, and his Kingdom built up, to the weakning of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the Reformed Intereſt. Beſides the Good that is loſt, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries procured hereby, the ſinfulneſs of Heart-Diviſions among Good men is greatly aggravated. The Provocation to mutual Revenge, and the advantage given to <hi>Popery,</hi> is that I wiſh all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> would conſider. As to <hi>Revenge,</hi> our Experience now tells us, that it is an effect of ſuch proceedings: tho I wiſh it could be ſuppreſt and cured; yet, conſidering the Corruption of Humane nature, might well enough be expected. This <hi>Dr. B.</hi> in the <hi>Preface</hi> above mention'd, hath repreſented with ſome ſharpneſs.
<q>How unreaſonable is it, ſaith he, that they, who cannot help thinking as they do, ſhould be made a ſacrifice to the Rage of others, who perhaps have little more to ſay for themſelves, than that they are in the Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Law:</hi> which in the next Revolution of Affairs that may fall out, will be an argument ſo much the ſtronger for uſing themſelves
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106978:29"/>in the ſame manner, becauſe it is a juſt Retaliation on them, for that which they made others to ſuffer —.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend and Worthy <hi>Dean of Canterbury</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Bp. Wilkins</hi>'s Sermons, commending his <hi>Moderation,</hi> ſaith
<q>That Vertue, however of late declaim'd againſt, muſt be the Temper of the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> if ever they ſeriouſly intend its firm eſtabliſhment: and do not induſtriouſly deſign by cheriſhing Heats and Diviſions among our ſelves, to let in <hi>Popery</hi> at thoſe Breaches.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt of thoſe who renounce our Religion, and imbrace Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, profeſs this to be the firſt great ſtumbling block, the want of Unity.</p>
            <p>This their Prieſts of late in ſeveral Pamphlets have inſiſted on, <note place="margin">Dr <hi>Stilling</hi> Idolatry of the Rom. Church. ch 5. Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ſafe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>and other Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi>
               </note> aggravating our <hi>Diviſions</hi> to prove the Neceſſity of an <hi>Infallible Judge</hi> as the Center of Unity. How unreaſonably this is urged by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who differ among themſelves about Fundamental Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Faith, many of our Divines have ſhown. However the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath manifeſtly ſerv'd its own ends by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing and animating the rigid Impoſition of doubtful diſputable terms among <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> that all thoſe who could not conform to the eſtabliſht Rites, might be look't upon, if not as bad as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> yet as unpeaceable and Factious, and be provok't to do ſomewhat that might make them as unfit to be tolerated. Hereupon the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have pleaded for themſelves as better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or deſerving at leaſt an equal Toleration with Proteſtant Diſſenters. And what ſome of the latter have ſuffer'd on the account of their different ſentiments from the Eſtabliſhed Church, hath tempted them to ſo much <hi>Revenge,</hi> as that the leſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and judicious are too ready to joyn with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or any body, rather than with thoſe by whom they have been op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt thô this be greatly to be lamented, yet it cannot much be wonder'd at; for <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us, that <hi>Oppreſſion will make</hi> even <hi>a wiſe mad Mad,</hi> And is it ſtrange that ſome who do not ſee far before them, nor well conſider what they do, and what forgiveneſs the Goſpel requires, ſhould be ready to ſay, we were as good joyn with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who promiſe us our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, than adventure to be Ruin'd by <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> That there is not now much ground to fear it, and therefore that no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ought to act on ſuch a ſuppoſition, I ſhall endeavor to ſhow preſently.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:106978:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>Adverſaries</hi> of the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion againſt us, notwithſtanding the Differences among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, deſerve to be conſidered. We read of ten or eleven ſorts of men of ſeveral opinions and ways in the matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, who all with one Conſent joyn'd againſt <hi>Sion. Pſal.</hi> 83.5, 6. Ten Kings of the Earth were of one mind, to give up their Power to the Beaſt, and make war with the Lamb, 17 <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. The Popish Clergy, that acknowledg the Headſhip of the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Man at <hi>Rome,</hi> agree in their deſires, and are bound to unite their endeavors, for the Extirpation of the <hi>Northern Hereſie, i. e.</hi> the Reformed Religion. And ſhall not we agree and unite, for the preſervation of that common Intereſt, againſt which ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a <hi>Confederacy</hi> hath been and ſtill is engaged? yea, <hi>may</hi> we not very well do ſo, <hi>Notwithſtanding</hi> our Differences, if we can but be wiſe and honeſt enough to forbear one another in love? Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of different Nations, habits, and cuſtoms, may engage in the ſame cauſe: and notwithſtanding their little quarrels with one another in their Reſpective Garriſons, may be unanimous (and therby Victorious,) when they come into the field. In a Battel between <hi>Hannibal</hi> and <hi>Scipio,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Livy.</note> when the two Armies joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we read that the <hi>shouts</hi> of <hi>Scipio</hi>'s men were far more <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible</hi> than thoſe of <hi>Hannibals,</hi> becauſe being all <hi>Romans,</hi> they had almoſt all the ſame tone of voice, whereas <hi>Hannibals</hi> Army being made up of ſeveral Nations, their ſhouting was <hi>leſs formidable</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Variety</hi> of their voices; it will not therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that their ſucceſs muſt be the leſs on that account. Our oppoſition to <hi>Popery</hi> might appear to them, and to the world, more <hi>formidable,</hi> if we were altogether of <hi>one</hi> ſpeech, and of <hi>one</hi> way, and our ſhouts more uniform; yet the <hi>Succeſs</hi> may be as <hi>Great,</hi> and the <hi>Victory</hi> as <hi>ſure,</hi> tho we are not, if we are but wiſe enough to bear with one another in our leſſer Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Since none of us do pretend to <hi>Infallibility,</hi> we have all the reaſon in the world to bear with one another. The principles of the Roman Church will better juſtifie them to demand a blind Submiſſion to all that is required, and to treat them ſeverely who refuſe it, than any of the Proteſtant Churches with reference to one another. We all acknowledg our ſelves liable to miſtake, and therfore ſhould uſe gentleneſs and Compaſſion to our Brethren,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106978:30"/>that we think do Err; and pity them upon the account of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailty and fallibility; which all would be more diſpoſed to do for others, had they a deeper ſenſe of their own. What two perſons in the world are juſt of the ſame Siſe of underſtanding, have the ſame apphrehenſions of things, or hold the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions? What man in the world, but as he grows elder, (and without loſing time, doth alſo grow wiſer) but alters his Opinions in many points? Do not various Educations, callings, Studies, Company, imployments, intereſts &amp; conditions in the world, make a mighty difference in the apphrehenſions of ſome from others, and of all men from themſelves at different ſeaſons? Beſides the various degrees of the grace of God to ſeveral Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, &amp;c. all which ſhould incline us, as fallible mutable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to bear with one another. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> teach, that an impliſit faith in the Judgment of the Clergy is ſufficient to juſtifie the belief and practiſe of the People, and ſo may better exact an Uniformity in Doctrine and Worſhip, than we who deny it; and hold, that every man muſt <hi>Judge</hi> for himſelf.</p>
            <p>It may farther be conſidered, that men cannot change their Opinions when they pleaſe, any more than their Stature or their Taſte. You may as ſoon fill a mans belly with a Syllogiſm, as alter his Opinion and Belief by Force, Till his Reaſon be convinc't, he will <hi>believe</hi> as he did. If any are willing to know the truth, and endeavor it, and practiſe according to their light, and deſire to live peaceably with others of a different perſuaſion; is it juſt and reaſonable, much leſs Chriſtian, that they ſhould be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and deſtroyed, becauſe they will not ſubſcribe ſome doubtful Articles, cannot ſit within the little Circle of ſome mens Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions that are uppermoſt, or conſent to worſhip God juſt after the ſame manner they would have them? Eſpecially they who ſtand out to their outward Diſadvantage, whoſe temporal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt pleads ſtrongly for a compliance; in ſuch a caſe, there is ground for Charity that they are ſincere. There is hardly any man but ſome time or other will allow ſuch Conſiderations to have ſome ſtrength.
<q>The word of God, ſaith Bp. <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, lect.</hi> 3. § 29.30.</note> doth Expreſly forbid us, to ſubject our Conſciences to any other, or to uſurp Dominion over the Conſciences of any. And there is no hope that Religion ſhould be reſtored to her former Original and Purity, till the wounds that have been made
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106978:31"/>wider by our quarrels and diſſentions, being anointed with the oyl of Brotherly love as with a Balſom, ſhall begin to cloſe again, and to grow intire into the ſame unity of faith and Charity.</q> Bp. <hi>Taylor</hi> hath much to the ſame purpoſe of moderation, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part</hi> 3. p. 420, 425.</note> (not to quote the many places in his <hi>Liberty of Prophecy,)</hi> in his <hi>Great Exempler,</hi> or Life of Chriſt, he ſaith,
<q>We ſhould ill dye for our Brother, who will not loſe a meal to prevent his ſin, or change a diſh to ſave his ſoul. And if the thing ſcrupled be <hi>Indifferent</hi> to us, yet it ought not to be indifferent whether our Brother live or dye. — When the <hi>Evil</hi> occaſion'd by the Law is greater than the <hi>Good</hi> deſigned, or greater than the Good that will come by it in the preſent Conſtitution of things, and the Evil can by no other Remedy be healed, it concerns the Lawgivers Charity to take off ſuch poſitive Conſtitutions, which in the Authority are meerly <hi>humane,</hi> and in the matter <hi>indifferent,</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Let us conſider the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonableneſs</hi> of our Diviſions, and backwardneſs to Union and Forbearance, at this Time. Neither the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor Proteſtant Diſſenters are ever like to have <hi>ſuch a time of Tryal</hi> again as this, when mutual Intereſt doth ſo loudly call for an Accommodation of our unhappy Differences. For not only doth the Heighth and progreſs of abounding Wickedneſs and Impiety require the utmoſt Union of Hearts, and Hands, and Tongues, to promote Repentance and Reformation; but we all do <hi>now</hi> ſee the miſchief of our paſt Diviſions; all Parties in their turns have been ſenſible of it. All have complain'd of a Spirit of Bitterneſs, Perſecution, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; and therfore none ſhould imitate that which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn; or be averſe to that, which ſometime or other they have thought deſirable. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 17. <hi>See Iſai.</hi> 9.21.</note> The Diviſions of <hi>Iſrael</hi> made them a prey to their Enemies; and thoſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> expoſed them to Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by the <hi>Romans.</hi> Which they might have prevented by an carly Submiſſion, or by uniting their Strength to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but by reaſon of their Diviſions, could do neither. So the conteſt between the <hi>Greek</hi> and the <hi>Latin</hi> Church ended in the Ruin of the Eaſtern Empire. And juſtly may God leave us to be deſtroyed of one another, or by the Enemies of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if we will not at laſt learn the way of Peace. Who
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106978:31"/>will pity us? who can help us, if having a prize in our hands, we will not know it, or improve it?</p>
            <p>Ought we not to conſider, that next to the Diſpleaſure of God for the ſins of <hi>English Proteſtants,</hi> this is the great <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the Church of Rome, and their moſt Conſiderable Advantage againſt us? We need not otherwiſe fear their other Politicks, (for which they have been ſo cried up in the World, tho prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally becauſe they ſcrupled nothing that would ſerve as a means to attain their end:) were we duly ſenſible of <hi>this one Policy</hi> of theirs, to divide, and exaſperate us one againſt another. The <hi>Preaching</hi> of their <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> will of it ſelf do little to turn the Nation to <hi>Popery:</hi> if we may Judge by their printed ſermons, they are not like to get much ground by their Preaching among a People, who in moſt places have been uſed to ſo much better. And as little need we fear their books of <hi>Controverſie,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the noiſe that hath been made of the Learning of the <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> their ſtrength hath of late been tried, to their irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſhame (if they are capable of any,) and as much to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the learned Divines of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Their Converting-books and Pamphlets have been ſo weak, and the Anſwers to them ſo ſtrong and ſo many, that they are not like to prevail much that way neither; if <hi>English Proteſtants</hi> would but bear with one another, and not ſeek <hi>Revenge,</hi> which the juncture of Time doth diſſuade from as unſeaſonable, as well as our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtianity doth forbid as unlawful, which will appear, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Whether it be not Improbable, that the Leading men of <hi>the Church of England</hi> ſhould hereafter commit the ſame Error again, to moleſt and Perſecute their Brethren for the Differences between us and them. All the world now ſees at what door a great part of the ſeverity againſt Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ought to be laid: (ſo far as it was the ſin of others, I hope God will let them ſee it, and give 'em Repentance.) And there are very many Pariſh Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> who are pious and peaceable, who preach and live holily, and never did conſent to the Perſecution of their Brethren, but endeavor'd to hinder it; I only wiſh they had been <hi>more.</hi> If it be ſaid, they are <hi>by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> Partakers of ſuch a guilt; it hath been, and muſt again be replied, that if God ſhould Charge undiſcerned Conſequences
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106978:32"/>upon them and us, none of us would be meet either for Church Communion now, or for Heaven hereafter.</p>
            <p>The paſt faults and miſcarriages of ſome, ſhould not make us injurious to others. Far be it from us to imagin, that there are no Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> but ſuch as are of our principles, and particular perſuaſion. Let us not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to love thoſe that are Good, becauſe many of their Church or Opinion are bad. Is there any Kingdom or Country upon Earth where the greateſt part are not bad? Is there any place where the Religion countenanc't and encouraged by the Government, hath not many who comply with it for ſecular Intereſt?</p>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>late Apology for the Church of England,</hi> as to the ſpirit of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> hath ſaid many things to this purpoſe: it will be good news to hear, that the greateſt part of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are of his mind: that all Prot. Diſſenters might believe, that the wiſeſt and moſt leading men of that Church, do ſee their Error, (their <hi>ſin</hi> too, might be added, if it be an eſſential Right of Humane nature, as Dr. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith, for every man to Worship God according to his conviction.) And we have great Reaſon to hope, that they will not again uſe ſeverity to their Brethren, if it ſhould ever be in Their Power; but come to a <hi>Temper</hi> in the matters of Conformity, as the ſeven Biſhops have under their hands declared their diſpoſition to do. And in the mean time; one of the <hi>Articles</hi> which the A. Biſhop of <hi>Cantcrbury</hi> hath recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Biſhops under his Juriſdiction, is a <hi>Tender Regard</hi> to their <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters:</hi> At the ſame time aſſuring us, and all the World, that they are really and ſincerely <hi>Irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Enemies</hi> to the Errors, Superſtitions, Idolatries, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies of the <hi>Church of Rome:</hi> and that all the unkind Jealouſies to the Countrary, have been altogether groundleſs.</p>
            <p>Let us not therefore be over ſenſible of paſt Injuries to the Hindrance of <hi>Concord</hi> for the common Good; leſt we wrong the Church of Chriſt, and neglect the ſecurity of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the wellfare of the Nation and of Poſterity, becauſe others have wronged us. For however the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> may now plead for Liberty of Conſcience, no Proteſtant (Brittiſh, or <hi>Irish</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) but muſt needs know, that of all Religions in the World, the <hi>Romish,</hi> by their avowed Principles, is obliged to be the moſt <hi>Cruel:</hi> Aſſoon as our diviſions have made us weak enough,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106978:32"/>we have but too much reaſon to expect it, which God Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Conſider that we Agree with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>great</hi> and <hi>many</hi> things, and thoſe things wherein we differ are comparatively <hi>few</hi> and <hi>ſmall,</hi> and therefore mutual forbearance and Concord is <hi>poſſible,</hi> as well as deſireable. Yea thoſe things for which they are Hated and ſtruck at by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are not ſuch <hi>Doctrines,</hi> or modes of <hi>Worship,</hi> wherein we <hi>differ</hi> from them; but 'tis for the ſake of <hi>thoſe things</hi> wherein we <hi>agree</hi> with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and therefore in prudence we are obliged to eſpouſe their cauſe, as our own.</p>
            <p>The Reader may eaſily perceive, that all that I have ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the Union of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> among themſelves, who, tho of different Perſuaſions in ſome External and Circumſtantial things, do <hi>hold the Head,</hi> 2 <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 19. and agree in the main and Eſſential Doctrines of Faith: But as to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the Chriſtian Faith, maintains and practiſeth <hi>Idolatry</hi> and falſe Worſhip, and the declared Enemy to all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and by her Conſtitutions doth oblige all her Members under an Anathema, to root out, and to deſtroy them as Hereticks: how far thoſe of her Communion may be tolerated in a Proteſtant Country, without ſin or Danger, is a matter too large at preſent to dilate upon. It would ſeem very ſtrange and Irrational for any Party of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to ſtrengthen the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and contribute to their being ſet up in Power and Authority, eſpecially in the Legiſlative power, in oppoſition to thoſe of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as fearing that <hi>theſe will not</hi> eſtabliſh and allow them Liberty of Conſcience; and imagining that <hi>the Papiſts will,</hi> who depend upon a forreign Power, and are not maſters of their own Conſciences, but have ſubjected them to another, whom they ſuppoſe Infallible. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> we ought the rather to believe and hope <hi>this,</hi> becauſe they have of late deſerved ſo very well of all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by a vigorous and learned oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Popery, in a great number of ſelect Diſcourſes upon all the Conſiderable points in Controverſie between us and the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> And having done ſo much to keep out Popery as to the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> let us hope, and pray, and charitably believe, that they will alſo do their utmoſt hereafter to prevent <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which is one of the worſt parts of Popery in <hi>Practice.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106978:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the pathetical Exhortation of the Devout Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi>
               <q>O Lord, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paſſion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> p. 390, 391.</note> how long ſhall thy poor Church ſee the dear ſons of her womb bleeding about theſe Apples of Strife? The Enemy is at the gates of <hi>Syracuſe.</hi> How long ſhall we ſuffer our ſelves to be taken up with Circles and Angles in the duſt? ye <hi>Men, Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Fathers!</hi> Help, for God's ſake put to your hands for the quenching of this Common flame; the one ſide by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, the other by Compaſſion, both by Prayers and Tears: Let me beg for <hi>Peace</hi> as for Life, by your filial Piety and duty to the Church of God, whoſe Ruins follow upon our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; by your love of God's Truth, by the Graces of that one Bleſſed ſpirit, whereby we are all informed and quickn'd, by the precious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lood of the ſon of God ſhed for our Redemption, be inclined to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> Tho our Brains be different, yet let our Hearts be one. — Let us have Peace with our ſelves, and War with none but <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Rome. Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
